COLLEGE
COLLEGE
this is a test
這是想驗
Our topic today is
我們今天的題目是
I'll see later
我等會會看到
It's Taipei Metropolis vs. Pompeii
是臺北都會 vs. 蓬佩古城
Then we invited to this court
那我們請到了本院
Researcher Lin Zhengxiong of the Institute of Earth Sciences
地球科學研究所的林鄭雄研究員
Come give us a special presentation
來為我們做這一個專題演講
I think everyone has heard of Pompeii
我想大家都聽過蓬佩古城
its an ancient city in italy
它在義大利的一個古城
more than 2000 years ago
2000多年以前
because of a volcanic eruption
因為火山爆發
So it was a very prosperous ancient city
所以當時很繁榮的一個古城
It's gone all night
就整個被夜沒了
Then we associate it with Taipei
那我們把它跟臺北扯在一起
It’s because it’s actually next to Taipei City
是因為其實臺北市的旁邊
there is a volcano
有一個火山
This is our special presentation today
這是我們今天特別專門的演講
I'm here to tell you about this
是來跟大家介紹這件事情
Our Datun Mountain is actually a volcano
我們的大屯山其實是一個火火山
so today's speech
所以今天的演講
Let's wait for Researcher Lin to explain
我們等一下林研究員會解說
How do we determine that our Tatun volcano is a volcanic volcano
我們如何來判定我們的大屯火山是一個火火山
Observations using our SeismicNet
用我們地震網的觀測
To prove the existence of the magma reservoir under the Tatun Volcanic Group
來證明大屯火山群體下的岩漿庫的存在
Then we cover how to use technology to work
然後我們介紹如何運用科技工作
The early warning data provided by these volcanic eruptions
提供的這些火山噴發前的預警資料
then do some analysis
然後做一些分析
and then be able to know that
然後能夠知道說
Fire volcano next to our volcano
我們這個火山旁邊的火火山
what is its current condition
它目前的狀況是怎麼樣
We want to be able to coexist with volcanoes
我們希望能夠跟火山能夠共存
These are very important things
這些越致是非常重要的事情
The whole of Taipei is next to the volcano
整個大台北就在火山的旁邊
so i want to introduce
所以我想先介紹一下
our speakers today
我們今天的演講者
Researcher Lin Zhenghong
林鄭弘研究員
Graduated from Institute of Geophysics, National Central University
畢業於國立中央大學的地球物理研究所
Institute of Earth and Environment, Institute of Technology
是美國人設立理工學院地球與環境研究所
PhD in Environmental Science
環境科學系的博士
Institute of Earth Sciences
目前是在本院地球科學研究所
Researcher and Deputy Director
擔任研究員兼副所長
Also National Taiwan University
同時也是國立台灣大學
Professor of Peace in the Department of Geological Sciences
地質科學系的和平教授
He is now in the Ministry of Science and Technology
他現在是擔任科技部
Director of the Tatun Volcanic Observatory
大屯火山觀測站的主任
and the Executive Yuan Central Disaster
以及行政院中央災害
member of fire prevention committee
防救委員會的委員
Researcher Lin's research focus
林研究員的研究重點
The focus of the past five years
近五年的重點
including the use of Taiwan's very intensive
包括利用台灣非常密集的
Earthquake Observation Network
地震觀測網
Let's talk about volcanoes
來探討火山
Two important sciences and landslides
與山崩兩個重要科學
Issues related to disaster prevention
與災防的議題
For seismic data
對於地震資料
innovative applications
進行創新的應用
So it will develop landslide monitoring
所以它會發展山崩的監測
principles and methods
原理跟方法
Others have a big contribution
其他有一個很大的貢獻
It is the building of the Tatun Volcano
就是建置了大屯火山的
His research has been awarded twice by the Ministry of Science and Technology
他的研究曾經獲得兩次科技部
or former National Science Council Distinguished Research Award
或是以前國科會的傑出研究獎
It is also the year of the Geophysical Society of the Republic of China
也是本年度中華民國地球物理學會
Geophysical Contribution Award
地球物理貢獻獎
and many other earth science studies
還有其他許多的地球科學研究
Related Young Food Paper Awards
相關的幼糧論文獎
So he brings a very interesting topic today
所以他今天帶來一個非常有趣的題目
We also have quite a few guests here today
我們今天也有在座相當多的來賓
Come on, everyone is very interested in this issue
來向大家對這個問題非常感興趣
I'm wasting too much time
我就多花浪費太多的時間
Let us welcome Researcher Lin Zhenghou with warm applause
讓我們以熱烈的掌聲來歡迎林鄭侯研究員
Vice President Ye
葉副院長
Thank you for your participation
謝謝大家的參與
hot summer weather
暑假很熱的天氣
Everyone also made a special trip here, very touched
大家還專程過來非常感動
that mainly i think
那主要我想
Of course, you may be interested in this topic
當然大家可能有興趣的就是這個題目
is we put
就是我們把
Laser Jam
Laser Jam
anyway good
Anyway 好
that's mainly this
那主要是這個
How can we in Taipei follow
我們台北都會怎麼會跟
Pompeii linked together
蓬佩古城連結在一起
That's actually this
那其實這個
especially in recent years
特別最近幾年來
We do a lot of work on the mainland site
我們在大陸網站做的很多工作
of course
那當然
This world happens to have
世界上剛好這個有
Pompeii film in 2014 also
蓬佩古城的電影在2014也
played
播放的
So the whole world is especially Taiwanese
所以全世界特別台灣人
special
特別的
Notice
注意
In fact, for such a topic,
那其實給這麼個題目其實
many of my colleagues
很多我的同事
or some friends say
或者一些朋友都說
My topic is too sensational
我這個題目太聳動了
so
所以
You give this title
你給這個題目就是
just want it
就是要
to trick everyone
要騙大家來的
Actually this topic is not
其實這個題目不是
I shouldn't have given it to you
應該不是我給的啦
conversely
反過來講是
Because I did work for the mainland website
因為我做了大陸網站的工作
So I went to many places regardless of assisting in speeches
所以到很多地方不管協助演講
or popular science speech
或者科普演講
In fact, after each speech
其實每次演講完
Mostly people will come to me and ask
大部分就會有人跑來問我
Will Taipei become Pompeii?
說台北會不會變成龐貝古城
So this is what a lot of people care about
所以這是代表是很多人關心的
then i hope today this
那我希望今天這個
This is more than an hour of these materials
這個超過一個小時的這些資料
After sharing with you
跟大家分享完以後
I think everyone will have the answer
我想大家就會有答案的
This very clear answer must be presented
這個很清楚的答案一定就可以呈現出來
especially in recent months
那特別最近幾個月
Last one or two years
最近一兩年
we'll start with this
我們就從這個開始講
At the end of last year, the Lihua Institute
這個立華院在去年底
Turn the volcanic disaster into Taiwan's
就把火山災害變成台灣的
like earthquake typhoon
像地震颱風
This natural disaster like flooding
這個淹水之類的天然災害
add volcanic disaster
把火山災害加進去
But everyone knows this is a new thing
但是大家都知道這個是一個新的東西
the past was never
過去是從來沒有的
That's because the Lihua Institute passed this amendment
那因為立華院通過了這個修法
Therefore, the Executive Yuan and local governments have many
所以行政院跟地方政府都有很多的
related action
相關的動作
especially taipei
特別是台北
Taipei at the end of March this year
台北在今年的3月底
Volcanic disasters that are also drills
也演習的火山災害
especially for
特別對於
These Beitou under the Yangming Mountain
這個陽明山底下的這些北投
The inhabitants of Tianmu
天母這些居民
let them know in case of volcanic activity
讓他們知道說萬一有火山活動的時候
It should be dealt with by the Shenbai District
應該審柏區應對
because in human history
因為在人類歷史上
Taiwan does not have volcanic disasters
我們台灣卻沒有火山的災害
Around us, the Philippines, Japan, Indonesia
我們周遭的菲律賓 日本 印尼
In fact, there are volcanic disasters at both ends of the three days
其實三天兩頭都有火山災害
Their people and the government have more ideas
他們的民眾跟政府都比較有些觀念
how to face him
怎麼去面對他
But Taiwan is really strange
但是台灣是真的很陌生
So hopefully we're not ashamed of the volcanic disaster
所以希望我們對火山的災害
have more understanding
有更多的了解
especially in recent months
那特別最近幾個月
This midnight volcano in Hawaii
這個夏威夷的午夜的火山
This Longyinliu is on the road
這個龍陰流就到的公路上面
Everyone knows Longyinliu
龍陰流大家都知道
It's very hot and very scary
這是非常高溫 非常可怕的
Anything that touches it is completely destroyed.
碰到什麼就完全就破壞了
If you go to Google and read a lot of reports like this
你如果去Google上面看蠻多的這種報導
Whether it's a direct lava flow or some breathing
不管是直接熔岩流或者一些呼吸的
Or poisonous gas, there are actually a lot of them.
或者有毒氣體啊 種種的其實非常多
In fact, here I would like to point out the following
那在這裡其實我特別要指出下面這個
This time, the eruption of this volcano
這個這一次這個火山的噴發
Caused a 6.9 earthquake
引發了一個6.9的地震
Well, this is actually something that the scientific community or many people are curious about.
那這個其實是科學界或者蠻多民眾都蠻好奇
Do volcanoes cause earthquakes?
就是火山會不會引發地震
Then Hawaii not only had a volcanic eruption in 1975
那夏威夷不只這一次在1975年那一次的火山噴發
Also triggered a larger 7.1 earthquake
也引發了一個更大7.1的地震
So what's the point of this?
那這個有什麼意義呢?
In fact, if you are interested in earth science or Taiwan
其實如果你對地球科學或對臺灣
If there are some concepts of these geology in northern Taiwan
北臺灣的這些地質有一些概念的話
In fact, it will be associated with saying that there is something next to the volcano on the mainland
其實就會聯想到說大陸火山旁邊就有什麼
We're actually pretty much the triangular fault that seismologists worry about
我們其實還蠻多地震學家擔心的三角斷層
Then some people talked about whether the volcanic activity would cause
那也有人講說火山活動會不會像引發
Triangular Fault Activity
三角斷層的活動
Evaluation of Triangular Faults by Experts and Scholars
三角斷層在專家學者的評估
If his entire triangular fault shifts
如果他整個三角斷層的錯動的話
The earthquake that is likely to be triggered is probably around 6.5 or 6.6
很可能引發的地震大概也是6.5、6.6左右
Although not very big compared with this
雖然不是很大跟這個比
But he is on the edge of Taipei city
但是他就在台北都會的邊緣
Well, according to some assessments made by the National Earthquake Engineering Center
那其實據這個國家地震工程中心的做一些評估
If the triangle fault is active
如果三角斷層活動的話
Thousands of houses in Taipei may collapse
台北可能有幾千棟的房子會倒
Of course thousands of lives were lost
那當然也有幾千個人命的損失
it's a potential threat
這是潛在的威脅
so of course this is extra
所以當然這是額外話
It's the relationship between volcanoes and earthquakes.
就是火山跟地震之間的關係
volcanoes cause earthquakes
火山會引發地震
Earthquakes trigger volcanoes
地震會引發火山
but not necessarily
但是不是一定
it's a matter of chance
它是有機率的問題
in some cases there will be
在有些情況上會有
Fire and rain in May
那5月下火雨活動
volcanic activity
火山活動
June 2
6月2號
Gualimara, Central and South America
這個中南美的瓜利馬拉
This is also the scene of the volcano
這個也是火山的景象
There can be these lava flows, debris flows
可以有這些溶岩流、碎屑流
you
你
Look at Xia Haorui's volcanic eruption
你看夏昊蕊的火山噴發
from the past few decades
從過去的幾十年來
hardly a single life was lost
幾乎沒有一個人命的損失
But relatively Central and South America
但是相對的中南美
Look at this a volcanic eruption
你看這個一個火山噴發
dozens of people died
就有幾十個人死亡
hundreds of people missing
幾百個人失蹤
Most of that believed to be missing
那大部分相信失蹤
Roughly equal to the number of deaths
大概等於是死亡的人數
then you can see
那你可以看到
This Central and South American and Xia Haorui
這個中南美跟夏昊蕊
why is there such a big difference
為什麼有這麼大的差別
In addition to the difference in volcanic characteristics
除了火山特性的不一樣
actually very important very important what is
其實很重要很重要是什麼
this
這個
Xia Haorui has done a lot of work
夏昊蕊做了很多工作
Japan has done a lot
日本做了很多工作
Volcanoes like Japan are often erupting
像日本的火山也是常常在噴發
But the threat to human life
但是其實人命的威脅
really very few
真的是少之又少
that's like this
那就像這個
June is the middle of last June
六月就上個六月中
Yindao volcano is erupting
陰島火山在噴發
that dragon smoke
那這個龍煙流
Because Yindao is across the sea
因為陰島隔個海
so to this
所以到這個
In fact, this city has no direct
這個都市其實是沒有直接的
Dragon Smoke, The Threat of the Cracked Hole
龍煙流 碎穴流的威脅
But volcanic ash is actually causing a lot of trouble, too.
但是火山灰其實也造成很大的麻煩
Then this Bali, Indonesian Bali
那這個巴黎島的印尼的巴黎島
This is also the last volcanic activity at the end of June
這個也是最近六月底火山有活動
Then some single things that cause the crowds of tourists
然後造成著旅遊的人潮的一些單物
Well, I'm actually going to tell a little story about this.
那其實這個我就要講一個小小的故事
It's the end of June this year
這是今年的六月底
In fact, Agong Volcano was in October last year
那其實阿公火山在去年的十月
If everyone has the impression
如果大家有印象的時候
He also sprayed once
他也噴過一次
Then this was two months before the eruption of Agong Volcano
那這個就當初在阿公火山要噴發的前兩個月
One day I arrived at the office at eight o'clock in the morning
有一天我早上八點多到辦公室
I got a call from this certain reporter.
就接了一通這個某個記者
radio reporter
電台的記者
he called
他打電話來說
Hello, Mr. Lin, I'm Momo reporter
林老師你好 我是摩摩記者
so and so
誰誰誰
Actually I can't remember
其實我也記不得了
Well, it's really because of too many reporters.
好 這真的因為太多記者
Then I said yes I remembered
然後我就說是是是我記的
He said let me ask you a question
他說我請教你一個問題
I said I thought there was another news
我說我以為又有什麼新聞
he said no
他說沒有沒有
it's a personal accident
這是個人的失事
The reason is that he is going to Paris Island
原因是他要去巴黎島
he wants to celebrate his birthday
他要慶生
25 or something
25歲還是什麼
Just invited a few friends to go to Paris Island to play
就約了幾個朋友要去巴黎島玩
As a result, when he was going
結果他要去的時候
Paris Island announced that
巴黎島就宣佈說
The volcano begins to stir
火山開始蠢蠢欲動
Then he called me and asked me if I wanted to go
然後他就打電話問我說要不要去
then i will talk to him
那我就跟他講說
This Indonesian survey
這個印尼的調查
Because I don't have the data
因為資料我也沒在手上
I don't understand very clearly
我也不是了解很清楚
but i told him
但是我跟他講說
if you are not in such a hurry
你如果不是那麼急的話
you may wait a little while
你可能稍微等一下讓
After Indonesia or the official announcement
這個印尼或者官方有一些宣佈以後
then you have to judge
那你再來做判斷
Then he probably listened to me
那他就大概聽了我的話
After two months
結果過了兩個月
another morning
一個早上又來了
he just called
他就打電話
I am a reporter from Mongolia
我是蒙古人的記者
He said sorry I am now
他說對不起 我現在在
Chung Cheng Airport
中正機場
then the night before
然後前一天晚上
that waited for two months
那個等了兩個月
The volcano has finally erupted to the surface
火山終於噴發到地表了
He said, should I go?
他就說那我該不該去
really two months
真正兩個月的時間
I said you are amazing
我說你還真厲害
you can really count the votes
你真可以計票一言
It was just when the volcano erupted.
炎的剛好就是火山噴發的時候
Then I told him that you might go
那我跟他講說你去可能
Maybe there will be a delay at the airport like this
也許會就這樣機場會有delay啊
But because the eruption of the Grand Agong volcano is the same as
但是因為阿公火山噴的那個跟
This Paris Island tourist place is about 60 kilometers away
這個巴黎島旅遊地方大概60公里
Maybe the volcano will have some impact on the airport
可能火山會對機場有些影響
But at least your life is safe
但是至少你的這個生命的安全
should have no scruples
應該沒有什麼顧忌
so he went
所以他就去了
so what does this represent
所以這個代表什麼
In fact, the volcano does not come instantly
其實火山不是瞬間就會來的
unlike an earthquake
不像地震
We can't predict earthquakes yet.
地震其實我們現在還沒有辦法預測
when will you come
哪時候要來
no one can tell
誰都說不上來
But volcanoes basically
但是火山基本上
Just like the Japanese and American
就像剛剛講的這個日本美國
or these Indonesian islands of Paris
或者這些印尼的巴黎島
they make some audience
他們做一些觀衆
In fact, I can warn you
其實都可以跟你警告
He started to move purely
他開始純准移動
you may have to prepare
你可能要做準備
or do something
或者要有什麼動作
So overall
那所以整個來講
In fact, the simplest way is to say
其實最簡單來講就是說
You may well imagine that
大家很可能會想像的就是說
this is our taipei
這是我們的台北
this is 101
這是101
This is a photo I took when I climbed to the top of the Jiuwu Peak
這是我爬到那個九五峰上面拍的一張照片
Then I put the ancient city of Pompeii and cover it with seven seven seven three
然後我把這個龐貝古城就把七七七三把它蓋住
will that be the case
那會不會這樣
It's something that many people imagine
這是很多人想像的一個事情
then we want to talk today
那我們今天就希望來談談
Pompeii and Taipei, or this, this, Dalun and Vesvi volcanoes
龐貝跟台北或者是這個這個大倫火山跟維斯維火山
do some comparisons what is the same and what is the difference
做一些比較他有什麼相同他有什麼不同
Then we'll know what happens to him
那我們就知道說他會有什麼樣的結果
So according to this very simple introduction, I will divide it into six parts to tell you about it.
所以根據這樣的很簡單的介紹我大概就分為六個這個內容來跟大家講
The first one is of course nothing more than introducing the relationship between Pompeii and Vesvi to everyone.
第一個當然不外乎就是把龐貝跟維斯維的關係跟大家介紹
We all know each other well
一起來大家都很熟
Maybe some people are a little blurry
那也許有些人稍微模糊一點
Let us now briefly introduce the space-time background
我們現在把時空背景稍微跟大家介紹一下
let everyone know a little bit
讓大家有一點認識
And the main part is when the volcano erupts
而且主要這一部分是說火山噴發的時候
Why did the entire city of Pompeii be submerged?
為什麼會造成龐貝古城的整個被淹沒
What kind of disaster, let's introduce it by the way
什麼樣的災害 順便我們把它介紹
Then the second is
然後第二個就是
Taipei and Datong volcanoes
台北跟大同火山群
Just now the vice president also said
剛剛副院長也講說
He is a volcano
他就是一個火火山
In fact, this is what we have done in the past 10 years
其實這是我們過去10年來的
Some like-minded friends in the academic circles
這個志同道合的一些學界的朋友
Results from different observations
從不同的觀測做出來的結果
Looks like he's a volcano
看起來他是個火火山
that especially myself for this
那特別我自己對於這個
The work of the magma chamber is actually
岩漿庫的工作其實是
took me a lot of time
花了我蠻多的時間
Sometimes I'm embarrassed to speak in private
有時候私底下不好意思講說
In ancient times, I heard people say
古時候就聽人家講說
It's a ten-year grind
是個十年磨一件
I have that deep feeling
我就有那種深深的感覺
I spent more than ten years
我超過花了十年的時間
Finally, do some questions that you want to answer
終於把想回答的問題做一些
find some answers
找到一些答案
The fourth part is
那第四部分就是說
TVO stands for Datong Volcano and Mountain
TVO就是大同火山跟山
Although volcanic
雖然火山活的
and threatening
而且有威脅性
But it's not such a scary thing
但是也不是那麼可怕的事情
as long as we are ready
只要我們有準備
That preparation is actually based on scientific monitoring
那準備其實就是靠科學的監測
Scientific knowledge can actually provide us with many coping methods
科學的知識 其實可以提供我們很多應對的方法
that fifth part is fun
那第五部分是好玩
This is not for fun
這個不是跟大家分享好玩
for me personally
對我個人來講
I studied ninth subject ninth science
我學了第九科 第九科學
And it specializes in the study of earthquakes.
而且是專攻就是地震的研究
When I saw the place name of this volcano and the heartbeat of the volcano
當我看到這個火山的地名跟火山心跳
I'm really a detective
我真的是探為官子
That heartbeat like a volcano
那個像火山的心跳
I believe no one in the world has seen
我相信全世界沒有人看到過
when i first saw
當我第一次看到
I don't think there is such a thing
我覺得怎麼會有這種東西
I will report to you later
那待會跟大家報告
Finally, a summary and discussion
最後就是一個總結跟討論
So I took advantage of this explanation with everyone's doctrine
所以我就發揮了這個跟大家主義的說明
Let's talk about Pompeii and Mount Vesve first
那先講這個龐貝跟維斯威火山
this is the italian peninsula
這是義大利半島
Rome, and south of it is the ancient city of Pompeii
羅馬 然後它的南邊就是龐貝的古城
Next to the ancient city is the volcano of Weiswei
古城的旁邊就是有維斯威的火山
that feeling is
那這種感覺就是
When the Roman Empire was very powerful
這個羅馬帝國非常強大的時候
good in every way
各方面都是很好
In fact, there are many achievements or VIPs.
那其實很多有成就或者VIP
very simple VIP
很簡單的VIP
It will be next to the ancient city here
它就會在旁邊古城這裡
to buy a villa
去買一個別墅
just come here for vacation
就來這邊度假
why come here for vacation
為什麼要來這邊度假
Actually, it's like this all over the world.
其實全世界大概都有這樣的現象
The volcano is the most beautiful
火山旁邊都是最漂亮的
like tokyo in japan
像日本的東京
everybody knows
大家都知道
Mount Fuji next to it is also about 60 kilometers away
旁邊的富士山也是60公里左右
That's the spirit of the Japanese
那是日本人的精神
Or fly to an impossible place
或者飛去不可的一個地方
that's actually like
那其實就像
I will bring it back to Taipei
我就把它拉回來台北
Where will the rich people in Taipei be
台北有錢的人都會在哪裡
You have to be able to afford some mansions
都要養得去弄一些豪宅
Because there are mountains and water
因為那邊有山有水
just beautiful
就是很漂亮
so like the whole world
所以就像全世界
as long as there are volcanoes
只要有火山的地方
basically just pretty
基本上就是非常漂亮
that is
就是
It's a place that makes you feel comfortable
就是讓你覺得很舒服的地方
but of course it has its threats
但是當然它有它的威脅性
2000 years ago
當初2000年前
The science of course is almost zero
這個科學當然是幾乎是零
So they didn't think of these things
所以他們也沒想到這些事情
So the ancient city next to it was built here.
所以就在這邊建了這個旁邊古城
If you have the opportunity to go now
那你如果現在有機會去
or have the opportunity to
或者有機會去
This is Vizvi
這是維茲威火山
This is the current appearance of the ancient city
這是古城的現在的外貌
After everyone is excavated
大家被挖掘以後
The rest becomes a very
剩下的變成是一個非常
A museum that many people visit
非常多人去觀光的一個博物館
or attractions
或者景點
Then of course the result of this is
那當然這個的結果就是
When Vizvi volcano erupted
維茲威火山噴發的時候
Think of this as the plot of the movie
把這個是電影裡面的情節
Just cover the entire ancient city next to it.
就是把整個旁邊的古城就蓋掉了
Then review these relevant knowledge
那回顧一下這些相關的知識
This Vizvi and the ancient city next to it
這個維茲威跟旁邊古城
In fact, the ancient city next to Vizwe is to the south of it.
其實維茲威旁邊古城在它的南邊
About 10 kilometers away
大概距離差不多10公里左右
That Huihui's representative said
那輝輝的這個是代表說
When the volcano erupted, the volcanic ash covered the entire area.
火山噴發的時候火山灰蓋的大概這個區域整個都蓋出了
So when it erupted in 2000, it was covered with 6 meters of volcanic ash
所以在2000年級噴發的時候整個蓋了6公尺的火山灰
In fact, nothing is gone
其實就什麼都不見了
At that time, the survey said that there were about 20,000 people living in Gai Gai
那當時的調查說大概有2萬人居住在蓋蓋
And with particular emphasis on holiday villas
而且特別強調的是在假日的別墅中
Everyone is very leisurely in the process of vacationing there
大家很悠閒的在那邊度假的過程中
It wasn't until the 16th century when the canal was opened that the ancient wall was discovered.
直到這個16世紀的時候開著這個運河的時候才發現有古墻
But in the 18th century
但是到了這個18世紀的時候
The king for these ancient artistic incentives
這個國王為了有這些古代的藝術的誘因
So he spent a lot of money to put this street in Pompey
所以他就花了很多錢把這個龐佩的街道啊
A lot of antiquities, just dig it out
很多古物啊什麼就把它挖解出來
That's why people know
所以才人們才知道說
This used to be a very large city
這裡曾經是一個非常有規模的城市
Although only 20,000
雖然只有2萬
But you can imagine 20,000 before 2000
但是你可以想像2000年以前的2萬
that was very lively
那是非常熱鬧的
a city
一個城市的
Then they dug this
那他們的挖出來這個
You see, the streets are very well planned
你看這街道都是非常有規劃的
futures-worthy
值得期盤式的
and especially this
然後特別這個
This is above the house of a giant merchant
這個有個巨商的房子上面
The money will be written on the ground
地上會寫說這個錢
this welcome money
這個歡迎錢
Welcome
歡迎你
It means they are extravagant
就是代表他們很奢侈
In fact, if you go to Google to find this document
其實這個文獻你如果去Google找一下
There are many, many criticisms
有很多很多的批判
It was the Romans at that time
就是當時羅馬人他們的
life of luxury or a lot of negative
生活的奢侈或者很多負面的
delay is in it
延遲都在裡面
Then of course the last
那當然最後就是
They don't know the money is waiting for you
他們也不知道這個錢等著你
But the volcano is there too
但是火山也有就在那邊
In fact, two sides of the same body
其實一體兩面
Then why did this happen in the end?
那最後為什麼會造成這樣
This is what we want to convey to you
這也是我們想跟大家傳達
What kind of threat does the volcano pose to me?
就是火山對我什麼樣的威脅
Then this is the original
那這個是當初的這些
These residents were instantly overwhelmed by high temperature
這些居民瞬間被高溫的
volcano
火山
When the volcano will also be buried
火山也會埋住的時候
In fact, your bone and flesh tissue is
其實你的骨肉組織就
disappeared in an instant
瞬間就不見了
but your body
但是你那個趨體就
become hollow
就變成空洞
So this is because they poured plaster into it.
那這個是他們是灌石膏進去
look like people at that time
把當時人的模樣
bailed it out
把它護援出來的
why is that so
那為什麼會這樣
In fact, I want to introduce to you
其實就是要跟大家介紹就是說
this pyroclastic flow
這個火山碎屑流
this
這個
this is real
這是真實拍的
Because Pompeii in the 2000s has
因為2000年代的龐貝古城已經
I can't prove it
沒辦法考據了
But volcanic activity
但是火山的活動
Actually
其實是
always have
一直都會有的
different places
不同地方
debris flow
就是所謂的碎屑流
what do you look like in this photo
你看起來這個照片就超像什麼
super like this
超像這個
Sand Leopard
沙塵豹
Anyway, it's just a cloud of ashes.
反正就是一團的灰那樣
so you can't see
讓你看不出
shiplike
船的
But this is totally different from the Dust Leopard
但是這跟沙塵豹是完全不一樣的
Sand Leopard
沙塵豹
look
你看
this is very fast
這個速度非常快
100 kilometers per hour 200 kilometers per hour
每小時100公里 200公里的速度
Then this is very hot
然後這個是非常高溫
hundreds of degrees of high temperature
數百度的高溫
It means you can't escape
意思是說你也逃不掉
if you are touched by it
那你被它碰到的話
actually probably
其實大概就
Just like the inhabitants of the valley of Pompeii
就跟那個龐貝谷城那些居民
almost identical
幾乎是一模一樣的
so you see this
所以你看到這個
this
這個
There are these villages and houses on the hillside
山坡上面這些有這些村莊 房子
actually
其實
you can imagine this
你可以想像這個一下來
In fact, there will be nothing left
其實什麼都不會留著
Pompeii Valley
就會跟龐貝谷城
exactly the same result
一模一樣的結果
That
那
you are all real
你這個是都是真實的
this is the philippines
這是菲律賓
brand apple
品牌蘋果
when the volcano erupts
火山噴發的時候
you can see right
你可以看到右
in the lower left corner there is a
左下角有一個
a little truck
有一點卡車
see this stream
看到這個碎穴流
certainly
當然
run if you can
能跑就跑
hop in the car if you can
能跳上車就跳上車
run fast
趕快加速的跑
But like I just said
但是就像我剛剛講的
Can these people escape?
這些人跑得掉嗎
basically can't run away
基本上是跑不掉
Because the flow velocity of the broken hole is higher than
因為這碎穴流速度比高
All road cars are faster
都是公路的車子還快
What's more, this is a path in the field
何況這個是田間的小路
that same year
那同樣在同一年
This silver circle volcano in Japan
日本的這個銀圈火山
You can Google this
這個你可以去Google一下
you can see this video
你可以看到這個影片
He is here, the car is here
他就人在這邊 車子在這邊
Run when you see the tax stream
看到稅息流趕快跑
Then the tax stream keeps coming and going.
然後這個稅息流就一直過來過來過來
Then the screen goes black
然後就螢幕就黑掉
Then why do you see
然後為什麼看到
Later, they took the camera out of him
後來人家把這個camera把他拿出來
Since that record is still
既然那個紀錄還在
he played it back
他把它playback
Then restore it to the process at that time
然後就把它還原當時的過程
So the tax and interest flow is actually for the volcanic disaster
所以稅息流其實對於火山災害裡面
it's number one
它是第一名的
it's inevitable
這是防不勝防
And you see it probably can't escape
而且你看到它大概跑不掉的
it's very very scary
這是非常非常可怕的
Then why is there a tax stream
那為什麼會有稅息流
This has a very simple cartoon explanation diagram
這個有一個很簡單的卡通解釋圖
Because when the magma keeps coming up from the crater
因為岩漿從火山口一直上來的時候
That's a thousand-degree high-temperature thing
那是上千度的高溫的東西
when coming up vertically
垂直上來的時候
after here it starts
到這邊以後它開始
It's going to cool down a bit, but it's still a few hundred degrees left
有點要冷卻 可是還是幾百度剩
But he starts off kind of turning into something solid
但是他開始就會有點變成固體的東西
It's turning into stone energy
就是變成石頭能量
Slowly feel a little cold
慢慢就有點冷卻的感覺
Then but when he keeps piling up
然後但是他一直往上堆高的時候
because of gravity
因為重力的關係
he will run to him at last
他最後會奔他
So when he accumulates a lot
所以當他累積很多很多的時候
when running to him for a moment
一瞬間奔他的時候
debris flow
就產生了碎屑流
Underneath are small rocks or these
底下是小石頭或者這些
large and small stones
大大小的石頭
volcanic ash
上面就是火山灰
then the whole thing comes down
然後整個就下來
So this is the one that threatens the most
所以這個是威脅人最多的一種
Then what I just said
然後剛剛講的
because it is high temperature
因為是高溫
so you see this just come down
所以你看這個只要下來
At this moment, the whole house burns down
這個瞬間整個房子什麼都燃燒掉
which one is the most
那一個最
most modern
最現代的
And the best example is
而且最好的例子就是
Ginsen Volcano in Japan
日本的銀仙火山
This is the eruption of this Yinxian volcano
這是這個銀仙火山的噴發
Then this is the Shimahara room
那這個就是島原室
at the foot of the mountain
就在山腳下
And then this debris flow comes from this hilltop
然後這個碎屑流就從這個山頂
Just go down the whole valley
就整個沿著這個山谷就下來
what happened
那發生什麼事情呢
something like this
就是類似這樣的
This is, the debris will come down along this ancient land
這個是 碎屑就沿著這個古地就下來
This lower digging is like a river
這個比較低挖的就好像河流
Mainly these crushed stones
主要的這些碎石頭
will walk along this low ancient land
就會沿著這個低的古地走
but here it takes a twist
但是在這裡它有一個轉彎
turn these stones
轉彎這些石頭
It's heavier, just go this way
它比較重 就沿著這邊走
but what does this arrow represent
但是這個箭頭代表什麼
It's just ash, a lighter substance
它就是灰 比較輕的物質
moshali it didn't touch the ground
它沒有碰到地的摩沙利
it goes straight from here
它直接就從這裡
just rush over
就直接沖過來
Then rush over here is the village
那沖過來這裡是村莊
There is a primary school in the village
村莊這裡有一個小學
we look at this elementary school
我們看這個小學
what happened
到底發生什麼事情
This is this crumb coming from here
這個是這個碎屑有從這邊過來
so we are
所以我們就是
Debris is coming from the back of this classroom
碎屑有從這個教室的背面過來
Of course you can see the glass
當然你可以看到這些玻璃
Everything is owned by that crumb
全部都被那個碎屑有了
Those ashes broke it apart
那些灰把它整裂的
Whole
整碎的
But if you look at the other side
但是你如果看另外那一邊
This is Li Doors and Windows
這個是李門窗
You can imagine how high that temperature is
你可以想像那個溫度有多高
That is the temperature of hundreds of degrees of volcanic ash
那個就是火山灰那個幾百度的溫度
When it came over in an instant, the entire door and window of Li, which was resistant to a considerable temperature, was deformed.
瞬間過來就把李門窗那個耐相當的溫度的整個都變形了
So if you imagine that this thing is very hot, the doors and windows are all deformed.
所以你想像說這個東西很高溫的東西李門窗都變形了
Then you can imagine people or all these houses
那你可以想像人或者所有這些房子
Ordinary traditional wood or houses burn instantly
一般的傳統的木或是房子一下子瞬間就燃燒掉了
In fact, Yingquan Volcano is in history
那其實營圈火山在歷史上面
In fact, it is a very, very painful lesson for Japan.
其實對日本來講非常非常多是慘痛的教訓
this 1792
這個1792年
Fifteen thousand deaths from this
這造成的一萬五千人死亡
why hundreds of years ago
幾百年前為什麼呢
This is actually one of these natural disasters worthy of our world
這其實是一個值得我們這個全世界的這些自然災害的一個
This model of understanding
這個認識的範本
what's going on
那這怎麼回事呢
when a volcano erupts
就是一件火山噴發的時候
Just like the eruption of the Xiahaoyi volcano just now triggered a
就像剛剛這個夏浩益火山噴發就引發一個
about seven earthquakes
大概七左右的地震
then the earthquake
然後這地震
Of course, we can imagine the damage caused by the earthquake.
當然地震的破壞我們可以想而知
even more frightening
更可怕的是
It put this silver inlaid on the other side there was originally a hill
它把這個銀鑲的另外這邊本來有個山頭
knocked it all down
整個把它震垮了
It just slides into the sea
它就整個滑到這個海裡面去
If it slips into the sea, it will generate a tsunami
滑到海裡了就產生海嘯
So this typical compound disaster
所以這典型的複合式災害
It's a volcanic earthquake and a tsunami
就是火山地震三分海嘯
The real 15,000 people may exceed 10,000
真正15000人可能超過1萬人
They all died from the impact of this tsunami
都是死在這個海嘯的衝擊
Then this is the silver inlaid volcano in Kyushu
那這個是九州的銀鑲火山
it's here
它就在這
So you see after this landslide falls into the sea
所以你看這個山崩到海裡以後
In fact, the seaside villages around the entire Inland Sea
其實整個內海的周遭的海邊的村莊
All residents suffer
居民全部遭殃
That's why there are so many mountain tiles
所以才會造成這麼多的山瓦
So the Fowles disaster is now more familiar to everyone.
所以富爾斯災害現在已經大家比較熟悉
Like Japan's Three World Wars and One Earthquake
像日本的三戰一地震
right
對不對
everybody knows
大家都知道
earthquake
地震
tsunami
海嘯
river disaster
河災
The river disaster may actually be
河災其實可能是
In fact, it is more endless than earthquakes and tsunamis.
其實是比地震海嘯更沒完沒了
So this event from the very beginning
所以就是從這個一開始的這個事件
but triggered to the end
但是引發到最後
In fact, the most serious is the last
其實最嚴重是最後頭
So this loaded disaster
所以這個負荷式災害
In fact, for what we are talking about now
其實對於我們現在在講
This disaster prevention is very important
這個防災是很重要的
if i know soon
我如果很快能知道
what happened to this
這個發生什麼事情
I have time to avoid subsequent actions
我就有時間去避免後續的一些動作
or some disaster
或者一些災害
So the loading hazard is
所以負荷式災害是
you are now the whole world for
你現在全世界對於
A very important concept of disaster prevention
防災的一個很重要的概念
OK, then say the same
好 那講這個同樣的
this of course hasn't happened yet
這當然還沒有發生
This is what many American advanced European scientists worry about
這是很多美國先進歐洲的科學家擔心的
This is Africa This is North America South America
這是非洲這是北美南美
That's here on the west coast of Africa
那在非洲的這個西岸這裡
there is a volcanic island
有一個火山島
The volcanic island is the same
那火山島同樣的
When they worry about a volcanic eruption
他們擔心火山噴發的時候
volcanic island will collapse
火山島會垮
or these terrific terrains
或者這些很抖竅的地形
As long as it collapses, there will be a tsunami
只要奔塌的話就會產生海嘯
that scientist
那這科學家
It's okay to do some simulations
這個沒事做一些模擬
but
但是
It's scary look at these numbers
怪可怕的 你看這些數字
it's 132 meters
這是132公尺
which city or 132 if we
哪個城市或是132 我們如果
132 meters, we may all soak in the sea here
132公尺 我們在這邊可能都泡到海裡面去
inside sea water
海水裡面
That
那
Although in the west of Africa
雖然在非洲的西邊
But New York, Boston or many cities on the East Coast of the United States
但是美國的紐約 波士頓或者東岸的很多城市
As long as this tsunami comes
這個海嘯只要過來的話
This is really out of hand
這個其實真的不可收拾
It is a great threat to human beings and the United States
對人類 對美國都是很大的威脅
Will this be an auspicious question?
那這個會不會發生吉利的問題
None of us can tell now
現在我們誰都說不上
But what day does a real volcanic activity turn into a disaster caused by a tsunami
但是哪一天真的火山活動變成海嘯造成的災害
auspicious
吉利
is a question worth thinking about
是值得我們去思考的問題
That
那
Although in Africa, every week seems to have nothing to do with us
雖然在非洲 每週好像跟我們沒關係
Then I take this opportunity to point out that
那我特別藉著機會指出來就是說
Everyone knows that Guishan Island
這個大家都知道龜山島
We didn't talk about Guishan Island today
龜山島今天我們沒有談
But Guishan Island is
但是龜山島是
Taiwan's outside of Big Butt Volcano
大臀火山以外的台灣的
volcanic activity volcanic island
火山活動 火山島
Guishan Island
那龜山島
if
如果
If you haven't been there, you can see that these terrains are very steep
如果沒有去過的話,你就看到這些地形就非常陡峭
If a volcanic event took this piece it arrayed it
如果一個火山活動把這一塊把它陣列了
This is of course a simulation like this
像這種這當然是個模擬
It also creates waves or tsunamis
同樣也造成海浪或者叫海嘯
In particular, our Yilan Plain is actually very flat, right?
特別我們的宜蘭平原其實非常的平對不對
A wave of 5 meters in the Yilan Plain may be a tsunami
宜蘭平原可能5公尺的海浪就是海嘯
Maybe the beach is the same
可能海邊的就照樣
If it is 10 meters, there is no need for 1.3 Yilan to be soaked in water
如果10公尺,沒必要1.3個宜蘭會泡在水裡
Of course we don't want this to happen
這個我們當然不希望發生
But things in nature are not about whether we like it or not
可是大自然的事情不是我們喜不希望
that we have to be prepared
就是我們要有準備
Can't wait until we wish it didn't happen
不能等到我們希望它不要發生就好了
ok , so let ' s go back to this volcanic disaster
好,那我們回到這個火山災
The downdrafts I just told you about are the scariest.
剛剛跟大家講的這些順氣流是最可怕的
That longan stream is like this shrimp fish
那龍眼流像這個蝦戶魚這種
The longan stream seems to be very hot, but it's not terrible
龍眼流像很高溫,但是它不可怕
There is one that is actually very slow
有一種其實它很慢
you see it , you run probably past it
你看到它,你跑大概跑過它
so longan flow
所以龍眼流
The damage is relatively limited.
傷害其實相對是很有限的
In addition, the earthquake we just talked about has also been mentioned.
另外就是我們剛剛講的地震也有提過
We're talking about volcanic ash and mudflows
我們就是講這個火山灰跟泥流
special volcanic ash
特別火山灰
The flowing dragons we just talked about are all at close range
我們剛剛講的這些流龍一流都是近距離的
it's only dangerous if you touch it
你碰到它才會危險
But volcanic ash is not
但是火山灰就不是
it can go far
它可以好遠好遠的
cause you a lot of trouble
就造成你很大的困擾
This was also last month
這是也是上個月
Yindao volcano erupts again
陰島火山又噴發了
Luer Island
旁邊的陸耳島
This is Yindao
這是陰島
This is Luer Island City
這邊就是陸耳島市
About Luer Island
陸耳島市大概
No more than about 500,000 people
沒比差不多50萬人左右
small city
不大不小的城市
this volcanic ash
這個火山灰
Yin Island is hyperactive
陰島是超活躍的
I go to Yindao
我去陰島
No more than 5 to 10 times
沒比5到10次吧
I don't remember either
我也不記得
but about twice
不過大概兩次
one time you will encounter volcanic ash
就有一次會碰到火山灰
I have a high memory
就記憶蠻高的
often just go and see
常常就去就看到
That volcanic ash is like a chimney in Asia
那個火山灰就跟煙囪亞洲
This Kagoshima city is like this
這個路爾島市就像這樣
This is either the sea or the volcanic ash
這個不是下海就是火山灰的關係
So Kagoshima city is very used to
所以路爾島市已經非常習慣
This volcanic ash lives with them
這個火山灰跟他們一起這個生活
Mount Aso two years ago
那兩年前的阿蘇火山
Just these cars in the whole neighboring city
就整個旁邊城市的這些車子
all covered
全部都被覆蓋住了
Of course it just makes your life very inconvenient
這當然只是會造成你生活很不方便
It will not pose a great threat to your life and property
還不會造成你的生命財產的很大的威脅
That's a small volcanic eruption
那這是小的火山噴發
But volcanoes have big eruptions and small eruptions
但是火山有大的噴發跟小的噴發
Like the Pinnatus in the Philippines that erupted here 900 million years ago
像九億年菲律賓的平拿土土在這邊噴發
This is where Manila is located
這是馬尼拉的位置
Pingna Tutu is in its northwest
平拿土土就在它的西北
This volcano has actually been in the past ten or twenty years
這個火山其實已經在過去一二十年來
Already a relatively large volcano
已經算比較大的火山
what effect it has
那它造成的影響
But this volcano is very lucky
不過這個火山非常幸運
why lucky
為什麼幸運
Because the United States has a so-called this in the Philippines
因為美國在菲律賓有所謂的這個
This Air Force GT is the Clark Air Force GT
這個空軍GT就是克拉克空軍GT這個
They were two weeks before the eruption
他們在火山噴發的前兩個禮拜
Because the USGS in the United States helped with the investigation
因為美國的USGS幫忙做調查
because of the problems with their F-16 fighter jets
因為關係的他們的F-16戰鬥機的問題
So they found out they couldn't do it.
所以他們調查結果說不行了
This volcano should erupt within 10 days
這個火山10天以內應該會噴發
All Clark Air Force GT F-16's are scrapped
所有克拉克空軍GT的F-16全部都廢走
only this one left
只剩下這一座
This is a broken plane
這個是已經壞掉的飛機
it can't run so keep it
它跑不了所以就留著
So a lot of volcanoes were built
所以就蓋了很多的火山會
This is a very successful example of a very successful volcano monitoring
這個是一個非常成功的火山監測的成功的例子
That is of course the result of the cooperation between the United States and the Philippines
那當然是美國跟菲律賓的合作的結果
then look at this
那你看這個
This though with these volcanoes at close range will
這個雖然在近距離有這些火山會
But this volcano will not only
可是這個火山會不是只有
nearby will affect
在附近會影響
You see this is the one before the eruption
你看這個是噴發前的這個
tens of kilometers of this
幾十公里的這個
Six layers of these ash
六層的這些灰
When it erupts in June, the whole thing turns red
六月一噴發整個都變紅色
The volcanic ash floats to very, very high altitudes
那個火山灰就飄到非常非常高的高空去
Then you see it's July, August
然後你看這是七月、八月
It was only in December that it slowly returned to its original position.
到了十二月才慢慢的又恢復到原地
So for about half a year, the entire volcanic ash floated high above the earth.
所以大概有半年左右的時間整個火山灰就在地球的高空飄
Although this is a relatively large volcano this year
那這個雖然是今年比較大的火山
But if a large volcanic eruption like geological time
但是如果跟地質年代那種大的火山噴發
could cover the entire atmosphere of the entire earth
可以把整個地球的整個大氣都蓋住
the sun does not come in
陽光不進來
Life on Earth may even become extinct
地球的生物或者甚至會滅絕
This is history
這是歷史上面有
That's what the historical evidence says
就是歷史上面的證據有說
The extinction of some organisms may actually be related to volcanoes
一些生物的滅絕其實有可能跟火山
Large volcanic eruptions are closely related
大的火山噴發有很密集的關係
Then in 2010 this Icelandic volcano
那2010年這個冰島火山
Maybe everyone has the impression
可能大家都有印象
The entire volcano will float to the continent of Europe
整個火山會就飄到歐洲的大陸
All flights across continental Europe are suspended
整個歐洲的大陸的航班全部都停擺
What about the whole passenger or the economy?
那整個旅客啊 或者經濟啊 什麼
They assess a whole bunch of losses
他們就評估一大堆的損失
Then this is a bigger volcano
那這個是大一點的火山
In fact, it's not just the effect of close range.
其實不是只有近距離的影響
In fact, all human beings will be affected
其實全人類都會受到影響
Let's see how much it erupts
那看它噴發的量有多大
Probably the biggest volcano is this one
那大概講大的火山不外乎這一個
This is the United States on the address
這個是美國在地址上面
they have three different colors
他們有三次不同的色彩
That's 2.2 million years
就是220萬年
1.3 million years
130萬年
640,000 years
64萬年
Area covered by three eruptions of different ages
三次不同年代火山噴發的覆蓋的區域
This geologist does career research
這地址學家做職業調查
outlined
勾勒出來的
So there's a super nutrition store under Yellowstone Park
所以在黃石公園底下有個超級的營養庫
This also has a movie in production
這個也有電影在產素
is also very sensational or very scary
也是非常的這個聳動 或非常可怕
So the United States actually treats this civil servant of the Huang family very, very seriously.
所以美國對於這個黃氏公務員其實是非常非常的認真的去對待
Why?
為什麼?
Of course, if you divide 2.2 by 3, it will come once every 700,000 years.
當然你把2.2除以3大概就是70萬年就來一次
So the last time it was 640,000 seems to be coming soon
所以上一次是64萬好像快要到了
If round by cycle
如果用週期來輪
If it is true, it means that they seem to be about to erupt in the tenth time in the tenth time
如果是真的話代表他們在第十年代的時候好像第十時間的時候已經快要噴發了
This is the result of a supervolcano
這個是超級火山的結果
Volcanic ash certainly has a big impact
火山灰當然就影響很大
Let's go back to this lahar
我們回到這個火山泥流
This is a volcanic mudflow in Colombia and the Americas
這個是哥倫比亞也周美洲的火山泥流
What is a volcanic mudflow?
什麼叫火山泥流?
Everyone knows that we have landslides in Taiwan
我們台灣有這個土石流大家都知道
It's just water, mud or he just flows down
就是水、泥或者他就流下來
It's even scarier at the volcano
在火山更可怕
volcanic ash is lighter
火山灰是更輕
so it is easier to flow
所以它是更容易流動
And the ash in the volcanic area
而且火山灰在火山地區
So as soon as you touch the sea, the whole mudslide will come
所以只要一下海就整個泥流就過來
Especially in these high mountains in Central America
特別這個是在中美洲這些高山
usually like jade mountain or this
平常就像玉山或這個
or higher these mountains
或者更高的這些山
it is covered with snow
它上面都蓋著下雪
But once the volcano came up,
但是火山一上來以後
It's just a high temperature and ice and snow
就是一個高溫跟冰雪
Touch some of that snow and it will melt
碰到一些那個雪就溶了
produce a lot of water
就產生大量的水
Then the water brings down the ash
然後水就把火山灰帶下來
The whole shock
整個這種衝擊其實
There are tens of thousands of people at every turn
動不動就是幾萬人這個
gone
就不見了
This is because it is far away from us in Central America
這個因為在中美洲離我們很遠
But in fact, the transmission of information
但是其實現在資訊的傳達
if you look carefully
你如果仔細去看
This is five years or ten years
這種就是五年十年
There is such a big disaster that will come out
就有這種大的災難會跑出來
The mud flow is like this the whole
那泥流就像這樣子整個
this
這個
Landslides in the South before Typhoon August 8
八八風災前南部的土石流
In fact, after blocking these rivers,
其實就把這些河道主塞以後
Then the water goes to the village to flood
然後水就到村莊裡面去泛濫城災
This is the moment of volcanic eruption
這個是火山繁發瞬間
Just now we thought that ash lahars
就剛剛我們覺得說火山灰火山泥流
Volcanic ash lava flow Water system flow
火山灰熔岩流 水系流
This is an instant disaster
這是瞬間的災害
But this mudslide
但是這隻泥流
this is endless
這是沒完沒了
Why
為什麼
just a typhoon
只要一個颱風
When the water comes, it will bring a mud flow
水來就帶一個泥流
especially the philippines
特別是菲律賓
Philippines at every turn
菲律賓動不動
as long as a typhoon comes
只要一個颱風來
Of course Taiwan is also often affected by typhoons
我們台灣當然也常常受到颱風
big threat
很大的威脅
But like the brand car next to me
可是像品牌車我旁邊那個
That is the volcanic fan has been carrying
那個就是火山繁就一直帶
poison the river
把河道毒死
Then the flood called the whole
然後就洪水就整個喚到
to many villages
到很多的村莊去
that may be 30 years
那可能30年
I can't take that volcanic fan away
那個火山繁還帶不走
that has always been
那一直就一直
repeat these menacing things
repeat這些威脅性的東西
Well, the Vesvi and Pompeii
好 那把維斯維跟龐貝
Or Volcano brings an introduction
或者火山帶來做一個介紹
we'll go right back to
我們就直接回到
Our Taipei and Chancellor Hill
我們台北跟大臣山
Of course this is imaginary
那這當然是想像的
This is our 101 Dalun Volcano in Taipei Basin
這個是我們的101台北盆地大倫火山
If the Great Looming Volcano erupted
大倫火山如果噴發
If these lava flows, crater flows, or lahars
如果這些熔岩流 碎穴流 或者火山泥流
Anyway, after the advanced stage, they may all go to the Taipei Basin
反正先進後後可能都到台北盆地
Then if these lava flows block the mouth of Guandu
那如果這些熔岩流把關渡這個口堵住了
Danshui and Keelung can't get out
那淡水和基隆出不去
Will there be this legendary Kangxi Taipei Lake?
是不是會有這個傳說的康熙台北湖
won't run out
也不會跑出來
This is a possibility as long as it happens
這只要發生就有這個可能性
In fact, I really hope to compare 101 with Qixing Mountain at this distance.
那這個距離其實我很希望把101跟七星山
Seven Star Mountain is the area we think is most likely to be active
七星山是我們認為最有可能活動的區域
Well, it's actually less than 15 kilometers
那其實它是小於15公里
is a very very short distance
是非常非常短的距離
Very short straight line distance
直線距離非常短
You can imagine this volcano will come up
你可以想像這火山會一上來
The whole of Taipei is probably similar to that one
整個台北大概可能跟那個那個那個
The guided one has almost the same impact on the city next to it
引導的對於那個旁邊的城市影響差不多
Then we also do a little bit of simulation
那我們也做一點點模擬
This is assuming that there is a volcanic eruption in Qixing Mountain
這是假設七星山有火山噴發
What will happen to Longweiliu
龍威流會怎樣
This is the simulated location
這是模擬的位置
Then you give me a little closer look
那你給我稍微靠近一點看
The different colors are its thickness
不同的色彩就是它的厚度
or its area of ​​influence
或者它的影響範圍
Don't look carefully at this
這個大家不要仔細看
because you will see where my home is
因為你會看說我家在哪裡
In fact, I have always
其實這一張圖我一直
I made it about four or five years ago
我大概四五年前我就做出來
I have never dared to show off
我都一直不太敢秀
Until recently because of volcanic eruptions it has been
直到最近因為火山噴發已經是
Legislated
立法了
when the government has to face
政府要去面對的時候
So this is just for reference
所以這個僅供參考
that's for
那是對於
If Huangzuishan
如果是黃嘴山
This is the bottom and this is the golden mountain
這是底下這是金山
just to the north
就是往北邊
We know Jinshan is very capable
金山我們知道很能場
In fact, many people are very concerned
其實很多人很關心
Will it affect the very energy field?
會不會對很能場影響
I don't comment on this
這個我都不comment
just do a little mock work
只是做一點點模擬的工作
Of course it will affect the range
當然會影響範圍
It all depends on the amount it erupts
完全看它噴發的量
If the eruption is a little bit smaller, it will certainly affect a small area
噴發的微一點點它當然影響範圍很小
If the eruption volume is large
如果噴發量很大
It certainly has a large reach
它當然影響範圍很大
that eruption is small
那噴發大很小
now we don't know
現在我們不知道
but i'll tell you later
但是我待會跟你講說
if it erupts next month
如果它下個月要噴發
I have a very high chance
我大概有很高很高的機率
will tell everyone
會跟大家講說
Will the eruption be big or small
會噴發是大還是小
This is based on some scientific estimates
這是有科學的一些估算的依據
Well, then this volcanic ash is also what everyone often talks about.
好 那這個火山灰也是大家常常會談的
This is some simulations done with the help of Mr. Wang Guowei from CUHK
這個是中大王國維老師幫忙做的一些模擬
In fact, he did it 365 days a year
其實他做了一年365天
Different directions according to different seasons
根據不同的季節不同的方向
when the volcano comes up
火山上來的時候
how it should float
它應該會怎麼飄
Then of course we have 365 days of data and we are running
那這個當然我們有365天的data我們在run
I'm here only spring and autumn
我這裡只是春天跟秋天
Of course spring, summer, autumn and winter are different
春夏秋冬當然不一樣
Every day actually has something to do with the direction of the wind
那每一天其實跟風向有關係
This is from our TVO 6 years ago
這個是在6年前我們這個TVO
We just want to say that if the volcano erupts that day
我們就想說那一天如果火山噴發
How should a volcano spread?
火山會應該怎麼擴散
Just go to Japan, and spread in the direction of Hainan Island.
就往日本、往這個海南島這個方向擴散
This is an impression
這是一個印象圖
Just tell these phenomena
就是告訴這些現象而已
Okay, we talked for a long time, actually.
好 那談了半天其實
This is what I've always wanted to say if if if
這都是我一直想說如果如果如果
if the volcano erupts if the volcano erupts
如果火山噴發如果火山噴發
But the real question is whether continental volcanoes will ever erupt
但是真的問題是大陸火山到底會不會噴發
So that's back to our serious scientific question
那這就是回到我們很嚴肅的科學問題
That is, we have been around for about ten years
也就是我們大概十幾年來
A group of people trying to find the answer
一群人去努力去找答案的
before finding the answer
那在還沒有找答案之前
When I was a student or earth science person
我當學生的時候或者地球科學的人
If you read it, you can probably know
念過的話大概就可以知道說
This is our topographic map of Taipei
這是我們台北的地形圖
The red area is the fire dust rock
紅色的區域就是火塵岩
Fire dust rocks represent the volcanic eruption
火塵岩就是代表曾經火山噴發的
lava on the surface
熔岩在地表
igneous rock body
就是火塵岩體
So this is probably like this
所以這個大概是這樣
That's because in Taiwan we don't have
那因為在台灣我們沒有
There is no record of volcanic eruptions in history
歷史上沒有說火山噴發的紀錄
So most people want to say
所以大部分人想說
Volcanic eruption, Taiwan does not do our business
火山噴發 台灣不干我們的事情
Taipei will never
台北永遠都沒有
But according to geologists, the stones in these red areas
但是根據地質研俠把這些紅色的區域的石頭
do some dating
做一些定年
The so-called dating is to find out the age of its eruption
所謂定年就是找出它噴發的年紀
Was it 10,000 years ago, 100,000 years ago, or 1,000,000 years ago?
是一萬年前還是十萬年前還是百萬年前噴
They can do it based on that parity year
他們可以根據那個同位數定年去做
Do the comparison and get the result
做比對 然後就得到結果
This is an old picture from the 1980s
這個就是大概1980年代的一張老的圖
That could have had a little eruption about a million years ago
那可以大概一百多萬年前有少許的噴發
By 800,000 years
到了80萬年的時候
Volcanoes began to emerge from the Chancellor Volcano
大臣火山就開始有火山出來的
then 400,000 years more
然後40萬年更多
Then came this 100,000 years
然後到了這個10萬年
feel like stopped
覺得好像停止的
So because the data is provided until 100,000 years
所以因為資料的提供到10萬年
There is no data for 0.1 million years
零點一個百萬年就沒有資料了
So there is no eruption in history
所以歷史上也沒有噴發
This geological researcher told us that it seems to be gone in 100,000 years.
這個地質研俠告訴我們說10萬年好像就沒有了
So for a long, long time in the past
所以在過去很長很長的時間
Minister Volcano
大家就大臣火山
Or Yang Mingzhang National Park is for fun
或楊明璋國家公園就是去玩的
he's not threatening to me
他對我沒有什麼威脅性
But about ten years of work
但是大概十幾年來的工作
If we go to mainland volcanoes to see
我們如果去大陸火山看到
This is a surface fumarole hot spring, right?
這是地表噴氣孔溫泉對不對
This is a typical volcanic area
這是滿典型的火山的區域
Especially this geochemical analysis
那特別這個地球化學的分析
This is the work done by the professors raised by the National Taiwan University
這是以前台大養上來教授做的工作
He is still equal to the pioneer
他還是等於先驅
He did some of these chemical analyzes of the fumaroles
他做了一些噴氣孔的這些化學的分析
just tell us
告訴我們就說
That thing is not a feature of the surface
那個東西不是地表的特徵
but what
而是什麼
If you step deep into the earth, you will come slowly
深步地球來的就是地慢
That's Teacher Yang Canran
那也是楊燦然老師
met me once and said
有一次碰到我說說
Geochemistry
地球化學
Chemically it looks like it's alive
化學的角度看起來它是活的
But no one does physics
可是物理的卻沒有人去做
so he advised me to do it
所以他勸我去做
At that time, I just returned from a one-year visit to Japan.
那時候我剛好去日本訪問一年回來
Saw a lot of volcanoes in Japan
在日本看了很多火山
I gladly jumped in and did it
我就欣然就跳進去做
Then I jumped in and now I can't come back
然後一跳進去到現在就回不來了
more and more miracles
越做越奇蹟
Then anyway, I will cast the Earthquake King
那anyway我就布了地震王
so i watched a lot
所以我就看了很多的
There are many, many earthquakes in Daren Mountain
在大人山就好多好多的地震
Then in these earthquakes
然後在這些地震裡面
What particularly attracts me is
特別讓我吸引的就是
There are quite
有相當的
This volcanic earthquake can be seen
這個火山地震看得到
The traditional one is an earthquake on a general fault
傳統的就是一般斷層的地震
Its appearance is similar to that of volcanoes and earthquakes
跟火山地震它的形貌
Its physical properties are completely different
它的物理特性是完全不一樣的
He has a person and he introduces several
他有一個人他介紹幾個
Then like this air-built radar
然後像這個空造雷達
see the crater burst
就看到火山口爆裂口
it's all new
這都是很新的
The rep said he wasn't weathered
代表說他沒有被風化掉
didn't get overshadowed by the 10th
沒有被第十年代把它掩蓋掉
mean he's new
意思是說他是新的
Then level the vehicle
然後水準車輛
it's a japanese one
這是日本的一個
one of my uncles
以前我的一個伯後
sit with me
跟我一起坐了
There may be a drop in the platform when it is found
發現地可會有台身下降
It means he seems to be moving
代表他好像有在動
rather than stable
而不是很穩定的
Then this dating
然後這個定年
Especially the last one is the most important
特別最後一項最重要
This is what we used to reason about
這是以前我們所理的
Chen Zonghua Deputy Director
陳宗華副所長
he found russia
他找了俄羅斯
found a german
找了德國人
I found it because Russia
找了因為俄羅斯
Then there are quite a lot of volcanoes
然後是有蠻多火山的
Then comes the year of the Volcano Society
然後就來火山會的定年
Because we don't have good experts in this field
因為我們沒有這方面的很好的專家
So I invite these foreign scholars to help
所以就請這些外國的學者來幫忙
He set out about 5000 to 6000 years
他訂出來大概5000年到6000年
Anyway, he made a mistake.
反正他有誤差就是了
But whether it's 5000 or 6000
但是不管是5000或6000
This means very high. What does it mean?
這個就很高的含義 什麼意思呢
In the neighboring country in 99 years
在鄰國99年的時候
We will open one at the Geological Survey
我們就在地質調查所開一個
Conference of experts and scholars
專家學者的會議
Then we talked about Taitai Volcano for a long time
然後我們就把大臺火山討論了很久
Although there are very strong disputes in the middle
雖然中間有極有很強的爭執
Some people say Yes and No
有人說Yes 也跟No
But the final conclusion is that
但是最後的結論就是說
general volcano
一般的火火山
Extinct volcanoes or volcanic volcanoes after the whole world
就是在全世界之後死火山或火火山
The result of our last discussion on Taitai Volcano
那大臺火山我們最後討論的結果
It's a dormant volcano
就是休眠的火火山
What is a dormant volcano
什麼叫休眠火火山
it is a volcano
它是火火山
but it's sleeping now
可是它現在在睡覺
someday you won't wake up
哪一天沒必會醒過來
What is the name of this volcano that appeared?
那這個現身的火火山叫什麼
like Xia Haoyi
像夏浩儀
You can go to see that magma anytime
你隨時去看那個岩漿
Or go to Aso Volcano
或者去阿蘇火山
it's smoking
它就在冒煙
boot smoke
引導冒煙
This is the volcano that appeared
這是就是現身的火火山
So the big round volcano is alive
所以大輪火山是活著
It's just that it doesn't look active right now
只是它現在看起來沒有活動而已
Then with this result
那有了這個結果
So this is the definition of volcanology, which means
所以這個是火山學的定義就是說
Active in ten thousand years
一萬年內有活動的
you have this record
就是你有這個紀錄的
I classify it as a volcano
我就把它歸類成火火山
just have a bad record
就是有不良紀錄的
special management
就要特別列管
pay attention to it
要去注意它
This is the experience above
這是經驗上面
But the phenomenon is
但是現象是
I personally feel the phenomenon
我個人覺得現象
maybe it has more scientific significance
maybe更有科學上的意義什麼
That is, if you can confirm that there is a magma chamber
就是你如果能確定有岩漿庫
like yellowstone park
就像黃石公園
the scientist said
那個科學家說
There is a big magma chamber underneath
底下有一個好大的岩漿庫
of course it's alive
那當然是活的
If Yellowstone Park just talked about
如果以黃石公園剛剛講說
last eruption
上一次噴發
The main eruption is 640,000 years old
主要噴發是六十四萬年
This is ten thousand years old
這個很大一萬年
That should be ten volcanic
那應該是十火山的
But Yellowstone can't use rules of thumb
可是黃石公園就不能用經驗法則
law of phenomena
就要用現象法則
It's the magma chamber that you found
就是岩漿庫你才找到
live without meaning
沒有意義就是活的
This is a general definition of something like
這是一個一般的定義上面的東西
So the process is
所以這過程就
In fact, for the past five or six years
我其實過去的五六年來
Every time because I do Daheng Volcano
每次因為我做大衡火山
Tell the Ministry of Science and Technology that this is a volcano
就跟科技部說這個是一個火火山
Looks like I'm a volcano
看起來是我火火山
At that time, the natural Sisi of the Ministry of Science and Technology
那時候科技部的自然思思長
Chen Yigao is also the 17th student of National Taiwan University
陳怡高他也是台大第十七的
we are still mature
我們都還滿熟
every time i meet you i say
每次碰到我就說
Where did you say the volcanic magma chamber is?
你說火火山岩漿庫在哪裡
When you meet me, ask me where the magma chamber is
碰到我就問我岩漿庫在哪裡
I was asked by him for five or six years
我就被他問了五六年
I actually want to talk more
我其實想講話比較多
In fact, I probably have a spectrum how to do it
其實我大概有一個譜怎麼做
but no evidence
但是沒有證據
Then I came up with a very simple concept
後來就想到一個很簡單的概念
Just use the shadow of the magma chamber
就是用岩漿庫的影子
The concept of this shadow is very simple
這個影子的概念就非常簡單
we see the shadow of this plane
我們看到這個飛機的影子
We don't need to look up to know
我們不用抬頭就知道
there is a plane in the sky
天空有一隻飛機
Because the sun hits the plane
因為陽光碰到飛機
Can't penetrate the plane
碰到飛機穿不透
There is a shadow on the surface
就有一個影子在地表上面
it's clear
就很清楚嘛
The X-ray in medicine is the same for everyone
那醫學上面這個X-ray大家都這個
This X-ray hits the bones and tissues
這個X-ray打過去這個骨頭跟組織
Because the absorption is different
因為吸收細緻不一樣
So if the finger breaks off
所以指頭要是斷掉的話
see the crack
一下就看到裂痕
So this is because of the X-ray test
所以這個是因為用X光來檢驗
difference between tissue and bone
組織跟骨頭的差別
Then earth science actually started more than 100 years ago
那地球科學其實在100多年前
There is such a concept that
就有這樣的概念就是說
when the earthquake happened
在地震發生的時候
Earth science has long known that
地球科學早就知道說
This external combination is AutoCore
這個外合就是AutoCore
it is a liquid
它是一個液態的
This is 2900 kilometers from the surface to the outside
這個從地表到外合是2900公里
is a very, very deep distance
是非常非常深的距離
But why do scientists know it's a liquid
但是科學家為什麼知道它是一個液態
It is based on the shadow of the S wave
就是根據S波的影子
Seismic waves hit the red part
地震波打到紅色的部分
you can see in this section
你在這個部分就可以看到
From this S wave signal
由這個S波的訊號
but you're on the brown side of the back
但是你在背面的這個咖啡色的這邊
You can't find a straight S wave
你找不到直接的S波
It was blocked by OtherCode
就被OtherCode擋住了
It's just a liquid substance, it can't go through it.
就是液態的物質它穿不過
S waves can't penetrate
S波沒辦法穿透了
Then maybe it's easier to tell you
那這個也許再簡單一點跟大家講
That is to say, this is the P wave
就是說這是P波
Whenever there is an earthquake
一有地震的時候
Anyway, elastic waves will produce P and S
反正彈性波就會產生P跟S
This is a heavy or compression wave
這是重波或者壓縮波
it's a bump
它就是一個撞一個
Look at this black
你看這個黑色就是
it shrinks and then stretches
它縮縮然後拉張
It's like hitting a pool ball
就是好像撞球一個撞一個
So the energy is transferred in one
所以能量就一個傳遞了
What is the S wave
那S波是什麼
S waves are like snakes
S波是像蛇一樣的
it just twists and shears
它就是扭動的就是剪切的
So one is a linear motion
所以一個是直線的運動
a sideways twist
一個是側向的扭動
Then this is of course simpler
那這個當然更簡單的
for simplicity
為了簡單化
That is to say, if the left side is a solid
就是說好如果左邊是個固體
on the right is a liquid
右邊是個液體
What is the difference between solid and liquid
固體跟液體有什麼不一樣
solid is this
固體就是這個
Between each molecule and the powder molecule
每一個分子跟粉研物分子之間
caught by chemical pieces caught well
被化學件抓住抓得很好
it can't run around
它不能亂跑
It means you're on my left and you're on the left
意思是說你在我的左邊就在左邊
you can't run to the right
你不能跑到右邊
but what about liquid
但是液體呢
You can run with liquid
液體就隨便你跑
is liquid or gas
就是液體或氣體
Meaning it doesn't have these brown sugars
意思是說它沒有這些糖黃
see you grab
就見你抓著
So what do these two different behaviors cause?
那這兩個不同的行為會造成什麼
P4 If you turn around from this side by external force
P4你如果外力從這邊轉過來
it will
它會
it will be like this
它會這個狀這個
and then this
然後這個狀這個
this shape this
這個狀這個
So P4 will transfer energy
所以P4會能量會傳遞
Then you when this one comes running
那你當這一個跑過來的時候
This S wave because it has sugar yellow
這個S波因為它有糖黃
it will pull over and the sugar yellow will elongate
它會拉過來它糖黃會拉長
so this will bring
所以這個也會帶過來
then take one by one
然後一個帶一個
So the S wave will pass like this
所以S波會傳遞這樣
So when solid
所以當固體的時候
Both P and S pass
P跟S都傳遞
but when liquid
但是當液體的時候
P4 can pass
P4可以傳遞
S wave because these two don't have any
S波就因為這兩個沒有任何的
that relationship
那關係
so
所以
This hole this one won't move
這個洞這一個不會動
Take a very simple ratio
舉一個很簡單的比例
everyone sit here
大家坐在這邊
if we hold hands
我們如果手拉手
is solid
就是固體
when one of them leans back
當其中有一個往後仰的話
The one next to it will also treat it
旁邊那個也會對它
so it will pull one by one
所以它會一個拉一個
So this is the characteristic of S wave
所以這個就是有S波的特性
If we don't hold hands, it will be liquid
如果大家不手拉手了就是液體
one of them lay forward
其中有一個往前躺
Lie forward, the one next to it won't be dried
往前一躺 旁邊那個它不會被乾
is a property of solid liquids
就是固體液體的一個特性
Based on this, we can test that
那根據這個我們就可以來檢驗說
Is there any liquid or solid in the earth?
地球裡面的有什麼這個液體或是固體的存在
this just
這個剛剛
Okay, so we imagine that
好 那我們想像中就是說
Except for Otocore, the earth is external and liquid
地球除了Otocore就是外合是液體以外
kernel
內核
Not this magma chamber
不是 這個岩漿庫
It should be that the magma with high temperature is liquid
應該是有高溫的岩漿是液體的
So I was thinking that S wave will definitely disappear after hitting this point, right?
所以我在想說S波打到這個一定會不見吧 對不對
Okay, then I have deployed a lot of seismographs here in Yangmingshan.
好 那我就在陽明山這裡就布了很多的地震儀
Then take advantage of the very deep bottom
然後利用就是底下的很深的
We have many large and deep earthquakes off the coast of Yilan
我們在宜蘭外海很多大的深的地震
and then straight up from the bottom
然後就從底下就直接打上來
then hit our area
然後打到我們這個區域
Then I'll check
然後我就去檢驗
You will see the blue seismic stations all can see the S-Bow
你會看到藍色的地震站都可以看到S-Bow
The only thing is that the red area cannot see S-Bow
唯一就是紅色的區域看不到S-Bow
Of course, P-Bow and S-Bow look a bit professional
當然P-Bow跟S-Bow看起來大家有點專業
but it's not that hard
但也不是那麼難
I put the red and blue records on the next one
我把紅色跟藍色的紀錄放在下一張
Here's where P-Bow arrives
下面就是P-Bow到達
Then the S-Bow arrives like it's clear
然後S-Bow到達很像很清楚
But when the seismic waves hit the magma chamber
但是當地震波打到岩漿庫的時候
P-Bow is penetrable
P-Bow是可以穿透
S-Bow can't find it at all
S-Bow完全找不到
It just disappears, disappears, and there is a shadow
就是不見了消失了就有影子
So this diagram says
所以這個示意圖就是說
S-Bow disappeared when hitting the magma chamber
打到岩漿庫的時候S-Bow不見了
S-Bow runs out when you miss it
沒打到的時候S-Bow就跑出來
According to this is very simple, we will draw a cartoon picture
根據這個很簡單我們就畫一個卡通圖
The magma chamber is here. If you hit yellow, this side station
岩漿庫在這邊如果打到黃色這個侧站
If you can't see it, you're blocked
就看不到就被擋住了
If this is true, we also repeat the verification that
如果這個是真的話,我們還重複驗證就是說
If the magma is fixed here, the S wave cannot pass through it, but what about the P wave and the heavy wave,
如果岩漿固在這裡,S波穿不過,可是P波呢,重波呢,
Heavy waves, solids and liquids are all fine, they can penetrate all of them,
重波固體液體它都沒問題,它都可以穿透,
Although it can penetrate, but it will slow down,
雖然它可以穿透,可是它會變慢,
Because it is liquid, it will go slower,
因為它是液態的,它走的會比較慢,
So I will walk here together as the side,
所以我會一起當旁邊的走到這裡,
These two it only goes so far,
這兩個它只有走到這裡,
This is a group of four, but it is very clear that we see the earthquake hit here,
這是四一組,但是很清楚,我們看這個地震在這邊打上來,
We got a signal on the surface,
我們在地表收到了訊號,
Then this is a simulation, if you hit the magma, it will slow down here,
然後這個是模擬,你如果打到岩漿固,這裡就會變慢,
Then the S wave disappears, and the right hand side is our observation,
然後S波不見,右手邊就是我們觀測,
That is, the wave that does not hit the magma solid will follow the distance,
就是沒打到岩漿固的波就會隨著距離,
Arrive here at the appearance of probably black,
在大概黑的出現這邊到達,
But once the magma is solidified, it will not be here, it is a little slower,
但是一打到岩漿固,它不會在這裡,是慢了一點點,
So when you look at the S wave, you can’t see it, and then the P wave is similar again,
所以你看S波又不見,然後P波又點類,
To me, this is the space of no doubt,
對我來講,這是毫無懷疑的空間,
There is a liquid substance under the ground,
就是地底下有一個液態的物質,
It is said that the liquid substance is, um, what is missing is magma, it is water,
那液態的物質有說,嗯,不見的是岩漿,是水,
That's impossible,
那不可能,
Why? At 20 km the water will be squeezed out
為什麼?在20公里水會被擠出來
Because the density of magma is closer to that of rock
因為岩漿它的密度跟石頭比較接近
it can be retained so it can't be water
它才可以保留 所以不可能是水
So of course magma is the best and only explanation
所以當然岩漿是最好的唯一的解釋
Then its size is about
那它的大小大概就是
GOO la 70 square kilometers
GOO啦 70平方公里
How big is 70 square kilometers
70平方公里大概多大
It's its area
就是它的面積啦
About a quarter of the size of the administrative district of Taipei City
大概四分之一個台北市的行政區大小
let everyone be grateful
讓大家有點感恩
A little bigger than Siling District, a little more than Xinyi Songshan in the East District.
比四陵區大一點比東區的新一松山南感
slightly smaller
稍微小一點點
what's the point of this
那這個有什麼意義呢
As long as one cubic kilometer of magma comes up
只要一個立方公里的岩漿上來
probably just like
大概就跟
It is so big before reaching the platform
還沒有到平台就鋪得那麼大
Maybe the deep sea is a little bigger than the deep sea eruption
可能到深海比深海崙噴發的大一點點
that would be terrible
那就超可怕的
So it's not like all this magma will burst the surface
所以不是說所有這些岩漿都會暴地表
Actually it's only 1%
其實它只要1%
A percentage of the earth's surface will actually cause a volcanic eruption
一個百分比的到地表其實就會火山噴發
So it's very dangerous
所以就很危險很厲害
Well, of course this is
好 那這個當然就
Because of the results of these studies
因為這些研究的結果
So the central
所以中央就
except the legislature
除了立法院
Then the Executive Yuan has done some
然後行政院有做了一些
this coping
這個應對
So a business plan for a volcanic disaster
所以火山災害的業務計畫
no matter central place now
現在不管中央地方
must follow above
都要follow上面
Some mechanisms of this strain
這個應變的一些機制
Alright, let's find out the sales and trading team
好 雖然把營業交易組找出來
but for me
可是對我來講
In fact, the challenge is greater
其實挑戰更大
The reason is that this is
原因是這個是
Our so-called colleague Huang Xinhua did it
我們所謂的黃信華這個同事做的
what to do at this yellowstone park
在這個黃石公園做
There is a extension library under it
它底下有個延將庫
there is a
上面有一個
that's in taiwan
那在台灣
I think it's 20 kilometers
我覺得在20公里
what we see is this one
我們看到的是這一個
actually more worried
其實更擔心
do you have this money
這錢的有沒有
That's because our resolution is limited
那因為我們的解析度有限
so I dare not speak
所以我也不敢講說
Is there any upper land?
上部地可有沒有
So the Ministry of Science and Technology gave me an order saying
所以科技部就給我一個命令說
keep looking
繼續找
we'll just mention one
我們就提一個
pretty big plan
蠻大的計畫
Make them like this for the ninth month
第九個月就讓他們這樣
we are in northern taiwan
我們就在北台灣
Ministry of Secret Codes for Seismic Stations
部的祕密碼的地震站
I hope that Datun Mountain and Guishan
希望把這個大屯山還有貴山
Find it in the magma chambers of these two volcanoes
這兩個火山的岩漿庫把它找出來
In fact, we also found the magma chamber on Guishan Island.
那龜山島的岩漿庫其實我們也找出來
The article is under review
文章正在審稿
should be out soon
應該很快就會出來
So there is definitely a magma reservoir under Guishan
所以龜山的底下也明確有一個岩漿庫
So we want to take this size depth
所以我們希望把這個大小深度
Hope to find it out
位置希望都把它找出來
So I hope to finish this project in four years
所以希望四年的時間把這個計畫做完
That's the black street station of our first year department
那這是我們第一年部的黑色的街站
Then the next year I hope to fill the white
然後第二年希望把白色的填滿
Then in the third and fourth years, I can really do some analysis and research
然後第三年第四年我就可以真正的去做一些分析研究
Next is this TVU
接下來就是這個TVU
This volcano looks like it's on fire
這個火山看起來是火的
eruption cannot be ruled out
噴發不能排除
what shall we do
那我們怎麼辦
This fear is often rooted in ignorance
這個恐懼常常就是因為無知
This is the Aso volcano just mentioned in Japan
這是日本的剛剛講的阿蘇火山
There are railroad houses and a lot of residents inside.
裡面有鐵軌房子什麼居民一大堆
This is a big crater
這是好大一個火山口
people live in it
人就住在裡面
lived for decades
住了幾十年
20 years, hundreds of years, maybe a thousand years
20年幾百年搞不好千年
they didn't panic
他們也沒有恐慌
live inside the crater
就住在火山口裡面
Where is that reason?
那原因在哪裡?
This one is more interesting
這一張更有意思
This is Chapelle May 1 spray 8
這個是夏貝爾5月1噴8
Director Chen of the NCD
那個NCD那個陳主任就
send me this one and say
把這一張就寄給我說
wow this is great
哇 這個超好
You see, this old beauty seems very handsome
你看這老美好像很帥
The volcano is covered in ashes
火山已經滿天的灰了
he plays golf there
他一樣在那邊打高爾夫球
The reason is that they are not afraid
原因是他們都不怕
The reason not to be afraid is not because you have courage
不怕的原因不是說很有勇氣
because of what ? with this backer
因為有什麼?有這個靠山
This is Chapelle Volcano off this station
這是夏貝爾火山關這站
Bottom this next to this
底下這個旁邊這個
Less than 100 meters to the crater
不到100公尺就火山口
When I visited last year, I asked him
我去年去訪問的時候問他說
How deep is your crater along the river?
你們這火山口沿江多深
He said 3 kilometers
他說3公里
I said wow, 3 kilometers away, you still dare to live here
我說哇 3公里你們還敢住在這邊
This has a history of 100 years
這個已經有100年的歷史
Why?
為什麼?
The volcano will erupt 8 will not be instant
火山要噴8不會瞬間
There will be action, there will be warning
會有動作 會有預警
so they can
所以他們就可以
so they are in good hands
所以他們掌握得很好
Therefore, they use earth sciences to monitor all kinds of air, surface or underground.
所以他們透過地球科學的不管空中地表或地下的各式各樣監測
as long as there is movement
只要有動的話
Before the volcano erupts, there should be
火山要噴發之前應該就會有
Like the one from Weisway just now, it is the oldest one a few years ago
像剛剛維斯威的這個是前幾歲最老的
18.4 billion years old
184億年就有了
This is a very old painting
這是很老很老的畫的
that is the status quo
那是現狀
Isn't this Pompeii already covered?
這個龐貝不是已經被蓋掉了
Why is there still a volcano observatory?
為什麼還要有火山觀測站
original intention is
原意是
sorry
對不起
Pompeii south of Visway
龐貝在維斯威的南邊
There is also a Napolis to the north of him
他的北邊還有一個拿波里斯
So this also needs to be Watched
所以這個也要Watch
to observe
要觀測
That day the volcano will
那一天火山會
unlucky for these people
這些人就倒霉了
so they have to monitor
所以他們要做監測
So we are at Datong Volcano
所以我們在大同火山
We're going to set up an observatory
我們要成立一個觀測站
This is the hardware provided by Yangmingnan National Park
這是楊明南國家公園提供的硬體
it's a nice environment
這是一個還不錯的環境
We have borrowed four or five offices here
我們在這邊借了四五個office
Then build this observatory
然後再建這個觀測站
At the beginning, the Ministry of Science and Technology and the Ministry of the Interior
當初就科技部跟內政部
Because the national public health belongs to the Ministry of the Interior
因為國家公衛的屬於內政部
We have a MEMO
我們就有一個MEMO
and then construct this
然後就建構這個
So the Ministry of Science and Technology paid the main money
所以科技部出了主要的錢
Our Chinese is also the main person
我們中文也也是出了主要的人
not only me
不是只有我
Many technicians at our Earth Institute
我們地球所的很多技術人員
researchers participate in
研究人員就參與
Ministry of Science and Technology
科技部這個
Hardware equipment from the Ministry of the Interior
內政部就出的硬體設備
Out of electricity, out of house, out of air-conditioning
出電 出房子 出冷氣
Because this is not actually a
因為這個其實不是一個
Very simple one unit can perform
很簡單的一個單位可以執行的
So we integrated a lot of
所以我們就整合了很多的
Then this is our observatory
那這就是我們的觀測站的
The location of the instrument distribution
儀器分佈的位置
This is the triangular fault just mentioned
這是剛剛講的三角斷層
This is the entire area of ​​Yangmingshan
這是整個陽明山的區域
Conceptually this is a picture
概念上是這一張圖
That is, we have spread a lot on the surface
就是我們在地表上面布了很多
different instruments
不同的儀器
Including seismographs Crustal deformation Geochemistry
包括地震儀 地殼變形 地球化學
ground temperature sprayed in
地溫噴進去
I always hope that as long as the volcano has erupted before
總總是希望說只要火山有噴發之前
We believe that there should be some anomalies in these
我們相信這些應該都會有一些異常
Then we have to report to the government, the people and everyone.
那我們就要跟政府跟民眾跟大家報告
Said the volcano may have started to restless
說火山可能已經開始不安分
This is our real-time monitoring station
這是我們即時的監測站
So we send a lot of real-time news to this screen for discussion
所以我們把很多即時的就傳到這個螢幕上面做討論
Then this picture is the enlarged one just now
那這張圖就是剛剛那個放大
This four-one picture is if people go up
這四一圖就是人家如果往上竄
In fact, the surface of the earth will deform the crust, right?
其實地表就會地殼就會變形對不對
be raised or arched
被台升或者拱起來
We have to rely on GPS to tilt the level
我們就要靠GPS傾斜以後水準有
we can measure the deformation of its crust
我們就可以量它的地殼變形的
And then here's like volcanic gas
然後這邊像火山的氣體
Because its concentration composition will also change
因為它的濃度成分也會改變
It is conceivable that the temperature will also increase
那溫度可想而知也會增高
that special seismic activity
那特別地震活動
Because my specialty is seismic activity
因為我的專長是做地震活動
that seismic activity is
那地震活動是
Of course I know best
我當然懂得最多
and I believe the most useful
而且我相信應該是最有用的
a concept map
一個概念圖
The usual magma has not changed for 10 kilometers, 20 kilometers I don’t know
平常岩漿沒變10公里 20公里不知道
Because the magma is hot
因為岩漿有熱
So there's a little bit of an earthquake on it
所以它上面就有一些少許的地震
But if the magma runs from A to B like this
但是岩漿像這個從A跑到B的話
Lava will come up
岩漿才會跑上來
what will happen to this incredible thing
這不得了的事情會發生什麼
Due to the change of temperature and pressure above
上面因為溫度壓力的改變
There will be many, many earthquakes
會產生很多很多的地震
For example, our Yangmingshan is now one month
舉例來講我們陽明山現在一個月
Maybe only three or five earthquakes every day
每天可能只有三個五個地震而已
If the magma goes up
如果岩漿往上跑的話
i predict or i imagine
我預測或者我想像
There may be 500 to 1000 earthquakes in one day
一天可能500個1000個地震
That's obviously different
那就很明顯的不一樣
Our record map is secretly referring to earthquakes
我們那個紀錄圖就祕密把它都是地震
I don't want to see but when I see
我不希望看到但是看到的時候
That means there is follow-up action
那代表就是有後續的動作
when the moon goes up
那它月往上的時候
This is called a volcanic eruption.
這個到地表才叫火山噴發
But you can say from B to C
但是你可以想說從B到C
When this earthquake B, the earthquake may be 3 kilometers
這地震B的時候地震可能3公里
There is one kilometer left at C
到C的時候剩下一公里
here maybe
在這裡也許是
5km or 10km
5公里或10公里
what does this mean
這代表什麼?
We only need the depth of the earthquake to determine it
我們只要地震的深度把它定出來
Must slowly change from deep to front
一定從深的慢慢變前
It's maybe 20 days from here to here
它從這裡到這裡 也許是20天
I know it runs 0.5 kilometers a day
我知道它每天跑0.5公里
If it is 3 days from here to here
這裡到這裡如果是3天
I just saw it run 0.2km a day or something
我才看到它每天跑0.2公里或多少
can i estimate
我可以預估嗎?
I guess it's okay
我就估算就是說好
That could be 10 days or a week to the surface
那可能到地表可能剩下10天或一個禮拜
so i can't tell you guys
所以我不能告訴大家說說
Will the volcano erupt next year?
明年會不會火山噴發?
This time is too far away, I can't follow
這個時間太遠 我沒辦法跟
But if say a month the volcano will
但是如果說一個月火山會
The volcano will erupt in a month
一個月後火山會噴發
I am sure I will see the exception
我相信我一定會看到異常
I'll see a spike in these earthquakes
我會看到這些地震的暴增
Of course it's not just an earthquake
當然不是靠地震而已
That is, the volcanic gas is immediately deformed, low temperature
就是火山氣體立刻變形 低溫
There should always be exceptions to this
總總這個應該都會有異常
When integrated, there should be good information to judge
整合起來應該會有很好的資訊去判斷
That also means that this is the approximate timeline
那同樣就是說這是大概時間軸
I can roughly estimate how long it might take to reach the surface
我大概可以預估可能多久會到地表
Similarly, if I see Huangzui Mountain
同樣 我如果看到是黃嘴山
Earthquakes are coming out of Huangzui Mountain
地震都在黃嘴山冒出來
I just want to say that Huangzui Mountain may approach the surface along the river.
我只要說 黃嘴山可能沿江快到地表
If it is in the big oil pit
如果是在大油坑
I knew that the big oil pit might move around along the river
我就知道 大油坑可能沿江蠢蠢易動
so i know something
所以我知道點
Then if I see a big oil pit, a small oil pit
那如果我看到 大油坑 小油坑
Why is Huang Zuishan so troublesome?
怎麼黃嘴山 什麼多事的話
The rep said, wow, it's serious all of a sudden.
那代表說 哇 之下子就嚴重了
it's comprehensive, right?
它是全面性的 對不對
So the size time
所以規模大小時間
Probably scientifically, I can make an estimate
大概科學上面我可以去做預估
So we did a lot of observations
所以我們就做了很多的觀測
But of course there have been no volcanic eruptions since
但是自今為止當然沒有火山噴發
it's very lucky
這是非常幸運的事情
But even if we don't have volcanic eruptions
但是我們即使沒有火山噴發
we do scientific research
我們做科學研究
We still found a lot of interesting things
我們還是發現好多有趣的事情
what is interesting
什麼叫有趣
we are earthquake
我們這是地震在
I will talk about the earthquake part
我就講地震的部分
this is
這個就是
Each line is a record of twenty hours a day
每一條線就是一天二十小的紀錄
A black is fifteen minutes
一條黑色是十五分鐘
and then the blue one for an hour
然後藍色的就一個小時
It's two hours, twenty-four hours
是兩個小時、二十四小時
Show you four or five hours in the middle of the night
給你看到半夜四、五個小時
The ground is shaking
這個地表一直在震動
When I first saw this ten years ago I wanted to say
一開始我十年前看到這個我就想說
That's the car
那就是車子啊
What is the wind and tide?
什麼風吹潮動啊
That is, there are many people in Yangmingshan anyway.
就是反正陽明山就很多人
but i want to say
但是我想說
The time pair is ten o'clock in the middle of the night to two and three o'clock in the morning
時間一對是半夜十點到早上凌晨兩點、三點
impossible to have a car
不可能有車子
unless it's something weird
除非是很詭異的事情
Well, based on science, we certainly believe it is
那以科學上面我們當然相信是
is to believe in science
是相信科學
So there should be no human activity
所以應該不會有人為活動
That should be this natural phenomenon
那應該就是這個自然的現象
So it's as simple as
所以很簡單就是
You can imagine if this pot is slapping and burning
你可以想像這個鍋子如果在拍燒
if heated
加熱的話
when the pressure builds
壓力變大的時候
Doesn't the lid of the pot cause steam?
那鍋蓋不是就會蒸氣的關係
will it vibrate all the time
它就會一直震動嗎
The vibration is likely to cause
那震動很可能就是造成
The concept that the entire surface of the earth is shaking
整個地表在震動的概念
That's also very interesting
那這個也是非常有意思
This is a certain earthquake
這個是某一個地震戰
is one, two, three, four
是一個、兩個、三個、四個
More than a dozen earthquake battles all counted a signal at the same time
十幾個地震戰都同時計到一個訊號
Then this signal is called to look like a drop
然後這個訊號叫做看起來像水滴狀
This is an earthquake record in the shape of a water drop in the scientific community
這是科學界就用水滴狀的一個地震紀錄
This is similar to the earthquake in Hualien, Chiayi, for example.
這個跟比如說嘉義花蓮的地震
completely different shape
形狀完全不一樣
These earthquakes in Hualien, Chiayi look
嘉義花蓮這些地震看起來
We look at P wave X wave Heptathlon people
我們看P波 X波 七項級的人
They all do this every day
他們都每天在做這個
But this one can't see the P wave at all
但這個完全看不到P波
X wave saw a very special
X波就看到一個很特殊的
Just like a drop of energy
像水滴狀的一個能量而已
Then if you look closely at its frequency
那你如果仔細看它的頻率的話
that's more interesting
那更有趣
it is single frequency
它是單頻的
it's about three to a few hertz
它是大概三點幾赫茲的
single frequency signal
就是單頻的訊號
How can there be a single-frequency signal in nature?
大自然的怎麼會有單頻的訊號
it's incredible
這是很不可思議的
That's easy, of course, let's talk about
那當然很簡單我們講說
Everyone play enough instruments
大家玩夠樂器
If you wave the strings of one of the lamps
你如果波其中一盞的弦
It's all single frequency, right?
都是單頻對不對
That means it looks like someone is rippling a string underground
那代表說地底下好像有人在波一條弦
Of course it's impossible
這當然不可能的事情
The real reason is that
那其實真正的原因是
Because the magma under the ground
因為地底下這些岩漿
it actually has these
它其實有這些
When the gas or liquid in these cracks
當這些裂縫的氣體或者液體
It only takes a change in pressure
它只要壓力的改變
or move quickly
或者快速的移動
The whole rock wall will shake
整個岩壁就會搖晃
The frequency of shaking is determined by its width and length
搖晃的頻率就是看它的寬度長度決定
like peeling a spin
就像剝一條旋那樣
If the thickness and length of its spin are fixed
它的旋的粗細長短固定的話
its frequency is fixed
它的頻率就固定
the width of the crack
那個岩縫的寬
Its geometry is the same as it is a single frequency
它的幾何一樣它就單一的頻率
This is really our interpretation
這個就是真正的我們的解釋
Rothstein
那也有像羅斯丁狀
super like rostin
超像羅斯丁
called English they called Tornitos
叫做英文他們叫Tornitos
this is very famous
這個是非常有名
Anyone who does volcanoes and earthquakes knows
只要做火山地震的人都知道
Why
為什麼
In Central America just those volcanoes
在中美洲剛剛那些火山
They usually see this first when they erupt
他們常常噴發的時候就先看到這個
Seeing this allergy has a volcano erupts
看到這個過敏都有火山就噴發
So this turns out to be an indicator of volcanoes in Central America
所以這個變成是中美洲火山的一個指標
but can't say
但是也不能說
Taiwan sees this volcanic eruption
台灣看到這個火山噴發
Because different volcanoes behave differently
因為不同的火山的行為不一樣
some volcanoes
有些火山
It can be used as a reference, but what we saw on Dalun Mountain
是可以當參考,但是大倫山我們看到的
It does not mean that the volcano is going to erupt, but it means that it is the color of some activities of the volcano
不是代表火山要噴發,但是它代表是火山的一些活動的色性
Then you look at its frequency which is more interesting, it is 2.1, 4.2, 6.3, 8.4
然後你看它的頻率更有意思,它是2.1,4.2,6.3,8.4
It's just a few special multiplier signals
就是特殊的幾個這個倍頻的訊號而已
Of course, this is also a ratio, as if you plucked 3 strings on the pipa
那當然這個也是個比率啦,就好像這個你去撥琵琶撥了3條弦
Those three different frequencies come out, so there can't be these options underneath.
那三個不同的頻率就出來,那那底下不可能有這些情選
The same is when you have an extension to a different column seam at the same time
同樣就是你同時有一個延長到不同的列縫的時候
A row of seams is a frequency, B row of seams is a series of seams with a frequency
A列縫是一個頻率,B列縫是系列縫有一個頻率
If it is blown at the same time, it will come out with some fixed frequencies when bitten.
它同時被吹給的話,咬起來它就有固定的一些頻率出來
There is also this low frequency, in fact its frequency is very low
那也有這個低頻的,其實它的頻率很低
Then this one is also very classic, the eruption of the Pinda Tubo volcano just mentioned
那這個也是非常經典,剛剛講的平達圖博的火山噴發
Do it for me on January 17th, at the erupting...
1月17日幫我做,在火山噴發的...
in the first ten days or so
在前十天左右
they see these things
他們看到這些東西
Hundreds of low-frequency earthquakes came out
幾百個低頻的地震跑出來
Finally they explained
最後他們解釋說
When the magma runs in the cracks of the rock
當岩漿在岩縫裡面跑的時候
low frequency signal
就會產生低頻的訊號
So this is also a good indicator
所以這個也是很好的指標
If Dalinshan we see
如果大臨山我們看到
a lot of this words
很多這個的話
It's also a big warning sign
也是很大的一個警訊
That also has the Cheung Chau flag
那也有這個長洲旗的
In fact, there are quite a lot of pigs of this kind.
其實豬的此類其實非常的多
I will speed up a little bit
我就稍微加快一點點
Then let's take what the chairman told us at the time.
那我們就把當初的主委交代的事情
Academician Mr. Li You
李游先生院士
Later, he was also the director of our Earth Science Rescue Institute.
後來也是我們地球科學營救所所長
After he chaired the committee here
他在這邊主委下來以後
Then we finish this volcano observatory
然後我們把這個火山觀測站完成
Of course the mission of the Volcano Observatory
當然火山觀測站的任務
mainly volcanic disasters
主要是火山災害
But it actually seems to be a negative
但是其實這好像是負面
But there are also positive
但是其實也有一些正面
this volcanic resource
這個火山資源
Seismic Development
地震開發
In fact, they are two sides of the same body.
其實都是一體的兩面
If we take these magma
我們如果把這些岩漿
These earthquake surveys are clear
這些地震調查很清楚
In fact, it can be applied
其實都可以應用
Two Yamada Production Axis
兩名山大大產軸心
what is it
就是什麼?
Huo Garden is very beautiful natural landscape
霍花園非常漂亮的自然景觀
There are also volcanic fumaroles
也有火山的噴氣孔
The hole of exile is a landscape unique to these volcanoes
流亡孔這些火山特有的景觀
different time periods
不同的時段
Huang Wen during the day
黃溫白天
very beautiful
非常的美
These are some photos taken by our TVU colleagues over there
這都我們TVU的同事在那邊拍的一些照片
It has snowed in the past two years
最近兩年也下了雪
It's also very rare
這也是非常難得的
The snow scene throughout our TVU
整個我們TVU的雪景
that hot spring
那溫泉
After these beautiful landscapes
有這些漂亮的景觀以後
If in the development of hot springs
如果在溫泉的開發
The development of four
四淡的開發
Could provide a better tour
可以提供更好的旅遊
An area for leisure
休閒度假的一個區域
Then these are these snow monkeys in Hokkaido, Japan
那這是日本的北海道的這些雪猴
they also know
他們也知道
Take a hot spring when it's cold
很冷的時候要泡溫泉
The largest seismic development is the
最大的地震開發就是
is Iceland
就是冰島
Iceland actually they
冰島其實他們
In addition to enjoying these hot springs
除了享受這些溫泉以外
They are also the world's geothermal development
他們也是全世界把地熱開發
About Iceland's Energy Roughly
大概冰島的能源大概
More than 80% are geothermal
八成以上都是地熱
So they don't need Henan factory
所以他們不需要河南廠
Henan plant does not need to burn coal
河南廠不需要燒煤
they enjoy the natural
他們就享受這天然的
Since Taiwan has these volcanic geothermal
那台灣既然有這些火山地熱
actually
其實
Conceptually, we should do some work here
概念上面我們應該往這邊做一些工作
So will continental volcanoes have geothermal development?
所以大陸火山會不會有地熱開發
In addition to volcanic construction
除了火山建設以外
In fact, I also spent some time thinking
其實我也花了一些心思
doing these jobs
在做這些的工作
We put up some seismic stations that look like
我們擺了一些地震站看起來在
There seems to be a big one here
在這裡好像有一個很大的一個
Hot discussion storage area
熱議儲存區
if science
如果以科學上面
This should be
這是應該專
Geothermal development should be a good place
地熱開發應該是個好地方
But I don't believe he's in a national park.
不過不信他是在國家公園裡面
This environmental protection regulation may also design customer service
這個環保的法規可能還要設計客服
but anyway
不過anyway
At the level of technology, we can do some related things
在那裡科技的層面我們可以做一些相關的事情
Well, the map part is more fun
好,地圖部分就是比較好玩的
this voice
這個聲音
This is actually the media or something
這個其實媒體或者什麼
You may also have the impression
你們可能也有印象
After a while, it was said that someone heard a strange sound
過一陣子就說有人聽到怪聲音
That's 15 years
那這就是15年的就是
someone heard something
有人聽到什麼什麼
Anyway, some descriptions mean that there is sound
反正一些描述就是有聲音的意思
Someone over here heard someone over here
那這邊有人聽到這邊有人聽到
In fact, when the media came to ask us
其實當初媒體來問我們
I probably have a score but it wasn't organized well at that time
我大概有譜但是那時候還沒有整理很好
so just pretend not to know
所以就假裝不知道
I probably know it all by now
現在就大概都知道了
also in history
歷史上也有
You see, this is 1835 and 53 years
這個你看就是1835年53年的時候
Three Days of Summer Big Butt Sandwich
夏日大臀三明三日
it will be very noisy
就是會很吵很吵
then we
那我們
Since we do these our TBO colleagues
自從我們做這些我們TBO的同事
Now I often call and say
現在常常會打電話說
The teacher heard the name of the place this morning
老師今天早上有聽到地名
It's just that some people can hear it and some people can't.
就是有些人聽得到有些人聽不到
of course
那當然
some say some don't
有些人說有些人沒有
is there any
到底是有沒有
we rely on evidence
我們靠證據
There are of course many reasons for place names
地名當然有很多原因
There are various other place names with earthquakes
有地震的地名有其他各式各樣
Today we're going to talk about the place names of Huo Zhan
我們今天就講火戰的地名
this is our sacrificial
這是我們祭奏
this is about five minutes long
這個大概有五分鐘長
But I'd say it's like five seconds or less
但是我把它說成大概沒比五秒鐘而已
The reason is because everyone may fall asleep after listening to it for five minutes.
原因是因為大家聽五分鐘可能就睡著了
The first reason is that if five minutes ago
第一個原因是說如果五分鐘前
In fact, its frequency is very low
其實它那個頻率很低
you can't hear
你聽不到
Because our ears are from 20Hz to 20,000Hz
因為我們耳朵是從20Hz到2萬Hz
normal person
正常人
If it is 10Hz
如果是10Hz
we can't hear
我們聽不到
just too low frequency
就是太低頻了
or too high frequency
或者太高頻了
So for everyone to hear
所以為了讓大家聽到
I call it a little time-lapse sound
我就把它稍微這個叫做縮時聲音
turn five minutes into five seconds
把它五分鐘變成五秒鐘
this is overclocking
這個是超頻
But the five flavors are just like a plane flying past
但五味就好像飛機飛過去而已
But this we based on these signals
但是這個我們根據這些信號
actually you see
其實你看
This is a different kind of earthquake warfare
這是不同的地震戰
Why Earthquake Warfare Receives Sound
為什麼地震戰會收到聲音
In fact, the sound is the vibration of air
其實聲音就是空氣震動
air shaken to the surface
空氣震動到的地表
our ruins on the surface
我們的遺跡放在地表
Shake our relics too
也會搖我們的遺跡
Because shaking the ground shakes the ruins
因為搖地面搖遺跡
relics will shake holes
遺跡就會搖洞
So let's take these cases into account
所以我們去計到這些情況
Then these earthquake shadows we can see
然後這些地震影我們就看起來
You see this is every earthquake video received
你看這個就是每個地震影都收到
Then we according to its sequence
然後我們根據它的先後
we can go and find out where it is
我們可以去找出它的位置
For example, we found it in a small oil pit
像這一個例子我們找出來就是在小油坑
very clear
非常清楚
I don't know if it's here or here
不知道在這裡還是這裡這裡
About 10 meters to 50 meters
大概差可能10公尺 50公尺
But it won't go outside the small oil pit
但是不會跑到小油坑的外頭去
Anyway, it's here in three minutes
反正三會兒在這裡就是
very sure
非常確定
This is just about one hundred and two minutes
這個就是剛剛也是大概一百兩分鐘
I put it like two seconds
我把它說成大概兩秒
you will hear
你就聽到
Actually, look carefully at this
這個其實你仔細看這個其實
This picture alone is enough to write an article
光這一張圖就寫了一篇
This, this, this scientific international article
這個這個這個科學性的國際文章
I will discuss this
我就談討這個
this is time
這個是時間
this is the frequency
這是頻率
This is when the whole thing explodes
這個是整個像爆炸的時候
Then before it explodes it has frequency from
然後爆炸之前它有頻率從
70Hz has been adjusted to almost 40Hz
70Hz一直調到差不多40Hz
The frequency is always deactivated and then detonated
頻率就一直遞解遞解然後就給爆炸
In fact, there is a very simple description, just like playing that heavy sky cannon when I was a child
其實有很簡單的描述就好像小時候玩那個重天炮
You chirp at one point and it explodes in the sky
你一點就啾然後天空中炸開來
That's certainly not a heavy sky cannon
那當然不是重天炮
This actually has good physics behind it
這其實它有背後有很好的物理
We probably don't have time to talk about deeper things
我們大概沒時間講比較深的東西
Xiaoerkeng is actually
小兒坑其實就
These things are often recorded
常常就會記錄到這些事情
That child's pit is more interesting
那小兒坑更有意思
This is the location of the children's pit
這個是小兒坑的位置
You climbed up to Qiqisan in Xiaoerkeng
你往小兒坑往七七三爬上去的
this is the trail
這是步道
You can see these little pits along the trail
你可以沿著步道看到這一個一個的小坑
Then it actually becomes a series of cracks
然後其實就串成一系列的裂縫
How did these cracks come about?
那這些裂縫怎麼來了
In fact, I know where these place names come from.
其實有這些地名我就知道是怎麼來的
Actually this is every
其實這是每一個
Just now the one that exploded like a heavy sky cannon
就剛剛那個像重天炮爆炸的
result
結果
mean to say
意思說
Of course, this small hole was not dropped when it rained.
這個小坑當然不是雨時砸下去
In turn it is a gas explosion from within
反過來它是從內部的氣爆
It's when there's a lot of pressure underneath
就是底下的壓力很大的時候
it explodes instantly
它瞬間像爆炸一樣
It's a hole when it explodes
炸開來就是一孔
so it goes along this fault line
所以它沿著這個斷裂帶
just a hole a hole a hole
就一個孔一個孔一個孔
It's just that the geological age has been exploding.
就是地質年代就一直在炸開來
That's how it flows on the surface
那流著地表就是成這樣
Then if you briefly show the entire fracture hole
那你如果簡示這個整個斷裂孔
These are all one by one
都是一個一個細的這些
It seems that these pits are connected when it rains
好像這個雨時坑的這些連起來的
very very many
非常非常多
The rep says it's actually been active
代表說它其實一直在活動
It's just that we haven't paid attention to it
就是我們一直沒注意它而已
Generally speaking, when we talk about volcanic eruptions, it is flames that come out.
那一般我們講說火山噴發就是炎漿出來
That like this steam explosion just wanted to look like
那像這種蒸氣爆炸就剛剛想看起來
That's the sound of that explosion
那種爆炸的聲音就是這樣
That's like Hawaii
那這種就是像夏威夷啊
Or a lot of it is the flame plasma to the surface
或者很多就是炎漿到地表
There are lava flows and broken cave flows
有熔岩流、碎穴流
what is this one
那這一種是什麼
It's just like Kaohsiung gas explosion
它就是像高雄氣爆那樣
exploded
一炸開來
only this
只有這個
That's why we can burn the pot and blow it up to gain strength
所以我們才能燒鍋炸開來力量而已
Then don't say it doesn't seem threatening.
那你不要說這個好像沒什麼威脅性
On January 3, 2014, he was an explosive
2014的1月3日他就是一個爭氣爆炸
He also caused the deaths of more than 60 people
他也造成了60幾個人的死亡
That death is really unfortunate
那這個死亡實在是很不幸的是
it's autumn and it's noon
這個是秋天 然後是中午
then he is saturday
然後他是星期六
Because this January 3rd is like our neutral mountains
因為這1月3日就像我們的中和山脈
Usually no one lives nearby
平常附近都沒住人
But the autumn wind is also super beautiful
但是秋天風也超漂亮
A group of people went hiking on Saturday
星期六一堆人去爬山
Then when I ran to the top of the mountain
然後跑到山頂的時候
Their habit is when they reach the top of the mountain
他們的習慣就到山頂的時候
reach the top of the mountain before noon
中午以前要到山頂
Come down for a crispy or bento
吃個酥脆或便當就下來
So it's almost noon and everybody's at the top of the mountain
所以到了快到中午的所有人都在山頂
As a result, the explosion at that time
結果那時候的爆炸
That's why six or seventy
所以才會造成六、七十個
if it's monday or three o'clock in the afternoon
如果他是星期一或是下午三點
a cat is fine
一隻貓都沒事
it's such an unfortunate thing
就是這麼不幸的事情
this is every day
這個就天天
This is Yang Mingzhang, we counted
這是楊明彰我們計到
because it sounds like a bird
因為很像鳥叫聲
is still in the woods
就是還在樹林的
this one is a little longer
這個稍微長一點
about two minutes
大概有兩分鐘左右
In fact, I have collected a lot of these
其實我就收集了好多好多這個
no i can't listen
不行 我不能聽
This is like a train
這個是好像火車
played the sound of a train
演出了火車的聲音
This is like a giant tree
這個像在巨樹
that's good
這樣就好
Then this giant tree just now
然後這個剛剛那個巨樹
Actually, I'm going to write another article
其實從事我要寫另外一個文章
Let's just talk about it. It's a volcano conversation.
就談這個 就是火山的對話
In fact, it is one by one
其實它這一條一條就是
This jet tube happens and the other is this one
這個噴氣管發生另外就是這一個
So A and B are over there
所以A跟B兩個就在那邊
sing together
一搭一唱的
super interesting
超有趣的
It's the dialogue of the volcano
就是火山的對話
Then this is Zhongshan Luo and Ziping after spraying
然後這個就是中山羅噴完就跟子平
Then it's like the two are talking
然後就是好像兩個在對話
The last one is
最後這個是
It was an accident that the dean of Guoyun
這是意外是國運的院長
I'll skip it first
我先把它跳過去
That's the sound of Dean Guoyun seeing my volcanoes
那是國運院長看到我這些火山的聲音
He went to the Academy of Performing Arts
他就去找藝術學院表演藝術的
He said this voice can be used as background
他說這個聲音可以當背景
they played for two hours
他們就演了兩個小時
Just those pictures over there
在那邊就剛剛那些圖片
I'm going to listen to this kind of wow, this is really exciting
我去聽這種哇 這個真精彩
This is the combination of science and humanities
這就是科學與人文的結合
final volcano heartbeat
最後火山心跳
Seismic.com has recorded many earthquakes
有地震網就記了很多的地震
nothing special
沒什麼了不起
But the funny thing is that we are here in Dayoukeng
但是好玩的就是我們在大遊坑這裡
remember hundreds of earthquakes
記得幾百個地震
What's so special about this earthquake?
這個地震有什麼特意呢
This is the new electrogram
這是新電圖
Every black line here is
這裡每一條黑黑的就是
This one is an earthquake station
這個一個就是一個地震站
Every earthquake also has a
每一個地震同時都會有一個
just an earthquake
就是有一個地震
So when an earthquake occurs
所以一個地震發生的時候
For all stations received
就所有測站都收到
This one bar after another is an earthquake
這個一槓一槓的就是一個地震
For example, if I look at a single one, it's fine.
比如我看單一的就好
single station you see
單一的測站你看
When each vertical bar
這每一個垂直槓的時候
just a small earthquake
就是一個小地震發生
Then this small earthquake turned out to be periodic
然後這個小地震它竟然是周期性
Hualien Earthquake
花蓮發生地震
probably no one can understand
大概沒有人可以理解說
when will the next earthquake occur
下一個地震哪時候發生
But I'm here to tell you
但是在這裡我去跟你講說
Now there's another 18 minutes
現在有個18分鐘就有另外一個
in 18 minutes
在18分鐘
do statistics here
這裡做統計
Of course not, it's just a few seconds off.
當然不是就是有幾秒的誤差
There will be one in these 18 or 19 minutes
這18、19分鐘就有來一個
This is about 1, 200 earthquakes
這大概一、200個地震
every 18 minutes
每18分鐘就來一下子
We know our new tickets are
我們知道我們的新票是
Seventy to eighty beats per minute
每分鐘七、八十下
But you count this 18 minutes
可是你就算這個18分鐘
Seventy or eighty times a day
每天七八十下
means he dances very slowly
意思說他跳得非常慢
But it's more interesting to say when this heartbeat started
但是更有意思說這個心跳從哪時候開始
He is from a 4.8 earthquake in Hualien
他是從一個花蓮的4.8的地震
When the earthquake wave reaches Yangmingshan
那地震波到陽明山的時候
heartbeat starts beating
心跳就開始跳
He's not Moby
他不是莫比奇妙跳
He looks like someone is going to wake him up and bite him
他是好像有人去叫醒他 咬他
It's time for a heartbeat
該心跳了
This is another Taichung earthquake
這是另外一個台中的地震
3.7 As soon as the earthquake came, Bobobo's heartbeat came
3.7 地震一來開始波波波心跳就來了
it happened three times
曾經發生過三次
Although there were three times I was super excited
雖然是有三次我是超興奮
Earthquakes are periodic
地震是有周期性的
This is something I've never heard of in the whole world
這是全世界我從來沒聽過的事情
then i will make a metaphor
那我就做一個比喻
normal heartbeat
就是正常人心跳
Then there is a problem with the image
然後就形象有問題
Start trimmer, start jumping wildly, stop jumping after jumping
開始trimmer開始亂跳一跳就不跳
then jump again
然後又跳一下
Then sent to the hospital, of course the electric shock
然後送到醫院當然就電擊
Shock again jump jump jump jump up
電擊又跳跳跳就跳起來
So the Hualien earthquake Taichung reporter seemed to be telegraphed
所以那個花蓮的地震台中記者好像電
So Yang Mingshan may have fallen asleep
所以楊明山可能睡了
It's just a new dance. I haven't danced for a long time.
就是新跳好久都沒跳
The earthquake shocked him and made him start jumping
地震把它電擊,讓他開始跳
But it's a metaphor, not a real thing
但這是比喻,不是真的事情
a fun thing
一個好玩的事情
It's this new jump that kills
就是這個新跳會收命
Animal Xiao Laozi jumped hundreds of times
動物小老子跳了幾百次
his life is short
他生命很短
Elephants are good at jumping very slowly
大象精於跳得很慢
then live longer
那就活得比較久
Of course that man is no longer an animal.
那人當然已經不是動物了
Humans are no longer ordinary animals
人就已經不在一般動物
This quote means
這個引意就是說
Anyway, the faster the new jump, the shorter the life
反正新跳越快,其實生命越短
Well if this extends it to volcanoes
那如果這個把它延伸到火山的話
In those 18 minutes, he danced super slow and super slow
那18分鐘,他是跳超慢超慢
so he can live a long time
所以他可以活超久超久
I'm unscientific
我這是非科學
a bit silly
有點瞎掰了
that last summary
那最後一個總結
we're back at mainland mountain
我們又回到大陸山
cooperate with this health committee
跟這個衛生委會合作
Metropolis and Old Town of Taipei
台北都會跟古城
Taipei City is a city of millions of people
台北都會是一個數百萬人
Of course Vesuvius, Pompeii, has 20,000 people
那當然維蘇衛這個龐貝斯有兩萬人
This is much worse
這個差很多
That's about 10 kilometers away.
那距離其實都差不多10公里左右
are very similar distances
是非常類似的距離
that is volcanic
那以火山的
The continent's volcanoes
這個大陸火山
This date may be 6000 years
這個定年可能6000年吧
But Vesuvius actually sprayed it again in 1914
但是維蘇衛其實1914年又噴過一次
The height of Seven Star Mountain and Vesuvi is actually over a thousand
那七星山跟維蘇衛的高度其實都一千出頭
That's mainly interesting
那主要有意思是這些
The area of ​​our magma chamber is about 70 square kilometers
這個我們岩漿庫的面積大概70平方公里
Vesuvius probably
維蘇衛大概
actually bigger
其實大了
6, 7 times
6、7倍
6 times is actually bigger
6倍其實就比較大
The top of the volcanic block is relatively large
火山塊頂比較大
The depth is relatively shallow
那深度它也比較淺
So we go a little deeper
所以我們深度稍微
deeper
深一點
but
但是
We are now trying to find out if there is a 5km or 10km
我們現在在努力再找看有沒有5公里10公里的
Magma reservoir
岩漿庫
then this is us
那這是我們
work in recent years
最近這幾年的工作
history in the sea of ​​course this
歷史在海當然這個
The side is also terrible
旁邊也是很可怕的
Yangmingshan no
陽明山沒有
The last one is what we want to convey today
最後這個是我們今天要傳達的重點
Whether it's a big volcano or a small volcano
不管它是大火山小火山
Population nearby or far away
人口在旁邊還是遠離
In fact, in the past, science can tell us
其實以前在科學可以告訴我們
you just do monitoring
你只要做監測
very easy thing
非常容易的事情
There is probably a considerable degree of protection
大概就可以有相當程度的保障
Monitoring is a simple matter in terms of science
監測以科學來講這是很簡單的事情
You just put the instrument down and do some analysis
你就是把儀器擺下去做一些分析整理
and then probably give us some
然後大概就可以提供我們一些
good reference instrument
很好的參考儀器
The ancient city of Weishuwei is here
維書威古城在這邊
But Napoli so they keep doing it
但是Napoli所以他們還是繼續做
This is a volcanic city
這個都是屬於火山城市
cities on or around volcanoes
就是城市在火山的上面或周圍
Taipei is also one of the volcano cities
台北也是火山城市的一個
the problem is that
問題就是說
Will the volcano move?
火山會不會動
we do not know
我們不知道
but we have to be prepared
但是我們要有準備
if one day it moves
如果哪一天它動的時候
we need to know in advance
我們要提前知道
That's the job of the Big Volcano Spectator Station
那就是大火山觀衆站的工作
so simple question
所以簡單的問題
I am often asked by many people
也是常常好多人問我的
So maybe now you guys can answer
所以可能現在你們可以回答了
Will the first one be active again? Yes
第一個會不會再活動?會
I usually don't dare to speak
我通常都不敢講會
I usually want to say that it cannot be ruled out
我通常都會想說不能排除
more like this
比較有這個樣子
And the second question is, will spending money be attractive? Yes
然後第二個就是說噴花錢會有意景嗎?會
everyone trust me
大家都相信我
I often give speeches here and there and tell people that's what I say
我常常到處演講跟人家講就是講這樣
But actually I'm pretty stressed when I go home
但其實我回家壓力蠻大
Where did it come from? A volcanic eruption
哪來的?火山噴發
I still haven't told everyone that I might
我還是沒跟大家講我可能
may have to kill himself
可能要自我了斷
And where did the millions of citizens flee to?
然後幾百萬市民逃到哪裡去?
This is the section chief of the Taipei exercise
這個是台北市演習的科長
been looking up i mean
一直在查我就是說
What should I do? What should Mr. Lin do?
怎麼辦?林老師怎麼辦?
He said where are our six million people going?
他說我們六百萬人跑去哪裡?
I said don't scare yourself
我說你不要嚇自己
There is no such thing as six million people, right?
沒有六百萬人這種問題對不對?
That Qiandu also wanted to say that we will move to Taichung.
那千督也很想說那我們就搬到台中去
The last question has an answer
最後一個問題答案都有
We should not be the ancient city of Pangbei
我們應該不會是旁備古城
In addition to many natural conditions
除了很多自然的條件
what is the most important
最重要最重要的是什麼
Time and space are different, right?
時空不一樣對不對
2000 years ago there was no science
2000年前沒有科學
people don't know what's going on
人民不知道發生什麼事情
but we now have science
但是我們現在有科學
Science can tell us many answers
科學可以告訴我們很多的答案
So the simple answer is no
所以答案很簡單就是不會
so this is the festival
所以這是節儀
just want us to be with the volcano
就是要我們要跟火山一起
Coexistence king but through science
共存王但是透過科學
Finally, I would like to thank the relevant units
最後就感謝相關的單位
Because this plan has actually been in the works for more than ten years.
因為這個計畫其實做了十幾年
It's this big plan that has been in the works for more than ten years.
就是這個大的計畫做了十幾年
The process is not a single
過程不是單一個
this this department
這個這個部會
or Chinese
或者中文也可以
can pay for all this
可以付的所有的這個
So we use various channels
所以我們就透過各種管道
and then go to convince people
然後去說服人家
give money to people
給地給錢給人
So let's build this volcano-official battle
所以我們來建構這個火山關政戰
ok this took a while
好這個拖了一點點時間
Very sorry
非常不好意思
Thanks
謝謝
Well, we thank Researcher Lin for a very good presentation.
好 我們謝謝林研究員非常精彩的演講
Now the rest of our time is open to questions
現在我們剩下的時間要開放給大家提問
We have prepared exquisite gifts on site
我們現場是有準備了精美的禮品
hand over here
在這邊手上
We have ten, so the first ten
我們有十份 所以頭十個人
If the first ten people ask questions, they will get a small gift
前面十個人提問的話會得到一份小小的贈品
There's that microphone in front of you guys
那各位前面有那個麥克風
wait a minute for a question
等一下如果要提問的話
please use the microphone
請你用麥克風
Click on a green part
按一下有一個綠色的部位
This will turn the microphone on
這個就會把麥克風打開來
now what's your question
現在請問各位有什麼問題
here
這邊
Hello Mr. Lin
林老師好
ok actually what i want to ask is
好 其實我要問的是
If an alert occurs
如果發生預警
There will be a volcanic eruption in the next ten days
接下來十天會有火山爆發
no results
結果沒有
seems more serious
好像比較嚴重
It's like a typhoon is coming, and it's a holiday
就像颱風來了 放了假結果
No, my question is actually
沒有 我的問題其實是說
The characteristics of Tatun Volcano are different from other volcanoes
大屯火山的特性跟其他火山
For example, are the volcanoes in Hawaii different?
譬如說夏威夷的火山特性有沒有不一樣
In other words, just ten days ago
也就是說剛剛的十天前
That dense vibration thing
那種密集的振波這件事情
In fact, I have no way to prove the Datun Volcano
事實上大屯火山我沒有辦法去證明
Really like that, time really explodes in the future
真的那樣的以後時間是真的爆發
unless it really explodes
除非它真的爆發
Then this experience comes from the situation of the volcano in Hawaii
那這個經驗是來自於夏威夷火山的情況
Will they be the same
那他們會不會是一樣
still may be different thanks
還是有可能不同 謝謝
this is a very good question
這個是非常好的問題
and you're an insider
而且你是內行人
Volcanic outbreaks are not 100%
火山疫情其實沒有百分之百
And every volcano behaves differently
而且每個火山的行為不一樣
In fact, the Hawaiian volcano and Mount Fuji
其實夏威夷火山跟富士山
Or that there are actually many types of volcanoes
或者那個其實火山有很多種種類
Hawaii is relatively annual magma
夏威夷是比較年至性很高的岩漿
so it just won't explode
所以它就是不會炸
This one was blasted
這個用噴發炸的
It actually flows more like water
它其實會像比較像水就流
That's like this volcano in the Pacific Rim
那像環太平洋這個火山
it will explode like
它就會像炸開了
That's because of its annual consistency
那原因是它的年稠度
Or we say its acid-base scientifically
或者我們科學上說它的酸鹼
Its ratio of that SIO2
它的那個SIO2的比例
you can imagine that
你可以想像就是說
as a pot of water
當一個一鍋水
rain is like a pot of water
下雨就像一鍋水
when you heat it up the water boils
你把它加熱的時候那水會滾
But if you cook a pot of porridge
但是你如果是煮一鍋的稀飯
or corn chowder with words
或玉米濃湯的話
when the viscosity is high
那黏稠度很高的時候
as soon as you boil it it will
你一煮煮煮它會
it will
它會
pop
啵
right
對不對
it's sticky
它那很黏稠
it keeps accumulating energy
它會一直累積能量
energy
能量
then it's about to explode
然後它就要炸開來
so different volcanoes
所以不同的火山
In fact, its composition is different
其實它的成分不一樣
it behaves differently
它的行為不一樣
So we can't put
所以我們不能把
Xia Yao Pooh or usual Toubot
夏耀維尼或者平常Toubot
or any volcanic act to bring
或任何的火山的行為拿來
Predicting what will happen to our big volcanoes
預測我們大的火山會怎樣
In fact, it is everyone
其實說穿的就是每個人
or each volcano
或者每個火山
has its own unique personality
都有它的獨特的個性
So we want to predict the behavior of a person
所以我們要預測一個人的行為
We can't put people in A
我們不能把A的人
past to predict B's
過去的去預測B的
In fact, the risk is great
其實這個風險很大
we better be
我們最好就是
Make a good observation and understanding of A
針對A做很好的觀測了解
See how it behaves
看它的行為傾向是怎樣
Then we make predictions based on this
然後我們根據這樣去做預測
but even so
但是即使這樣
we can't
我們也不可能
Actually there are
其實有
Several volcanoes have said that they think they will erupt.
好幾個火山都說 認為會噴發結果沒有
This is sometimes because of a very simple reason
這個是 有時候因為很簡單的道理
Your magma keeps going up and down, and your successor is unreasonable
你那個岩漿一直抬抬抬抬 後繼無理
In fact, Mount Fuji used to be this year in 2001.
其實富士山就曾經 這個2001年
Japanese scientists are extremely nervous with the government
日本的科學家他跟政府是緊張的要命
Why did they keep running from 20 kilometers away from the earthquake
為什麼 他們地震從20公里一直跑跑跑
After running 2 kilometers, he thought he might come up tomorrow or the day after tomorrow.
跑了2公里 他以為可能明後天就上來
be quiet from now on
就從此就安安靜靜
So this is still his
所以 這還是有他的這個
With this uncertainty, we can only do our best
這個不確定性 我們只能盡能力去做
Hello teacher, what I want to ask is
老師你好 那個我想要請問的是
It's the shadow of the S wave you mentioned earlier
就是你前面提到的S波的陰影
There is also P-wave's smoke call, which is the place where smoke call arrives
還有P波的煙喚 就是煙喚到達的這個
These two phenomena, these two phenomena are what I just said from the teacher.
這兩種現象 那這兩種現象就是我從老師剛才講的
I think all I know is that he reflects
我覺得我能知道就是他能反映出
He represents the existence of liquid substances under the ground
他是代表出 地底下有液態物質的存在
Then how can we infer from the existence of this substance
那從這義太物質的存在我們怎麼去推估
It is possible to estimate the volume of the magma reservoir and
它是可以去推估除這岩漿庫的體積以及
Is it the depth of these queries Thanks
它的深度這些質詢嗎 謝謝
The volume is calculated according to the surface of our land
體積我們就根據我們地表的策戰的
yes or no
有跟沒有嘛
We can probably heat up a range
我們大概就可以勾熱化一個範圍
that depth is a good question
那深度是一個好問題
Depth because of more scientific issues
深度因為比較科學性的問題
That is to say, I didn't talk much here.
就是說我在這邊沒有很講
That is to say, I use earthquakes at different depths for cross-comparison
就是說我用不同的深度的地震去做交叉比對
There is a little bit of this depth past and this depth
就是有一點這個深度過去的跟這個深度
If cut to yes or no
如果切到有跟沒有
That is, it has an angle, right?
就是它就有個夾角對不對
If at the very surface it doesn't have both
如果在很地表的時候它兩個都沒有
If it's 10 kilometers maybe it starts a little bit on this side and this side
如果它10公里的可能就這邊跟這邊就開始有一點
there is a gap
有一個差距
So take it slow
所以慢慢的去推估
But this is just a rough estimate
但這個只是粗估
That's why we have our second big plan.
所以我們才有第二個大的計畫
Hope to make more accurate
希望把更精準的做出來
So something like this
所以大概是這樣的
At present, the preliminary results can only reach this
目前初步結果只能到這樣
To make his relationship with that family from four angles
在四個角度去做出他的那個人家的關係
Because of this probably in the whole world I think I'm the first to do this
因為這個大概全世界我認為我第一個這樣做的
Because, for example, Mt. Fuji, theirs, or Mount Aso
因為比如像富士山 其實他們那個或者阿蘇火山
They are very clear about the evidence of Yeonjangku
他們就清楚的延將庫什麼證據非常清楚
people don't need to do this
人家不需要這樣做
That's because it's too controversial in Taiwan
那因為在台灣就爭議性太大
We can't see that thing on the surface
我們地表上看不到那個東西
That's why I worked so hard to come up with a way to verify it.
所以才千辛萬苦地想出這個辦法去驗證
So this should be the only
所以這個是應該是唯一
The only scientifically I know of anyone doing this
我目前知道科學上唯一有人這樣做的
yes
是
Hello Mr. Lin
林老師你好
I want to ask is in the past geological records
我想問就是在過往的地質紀錄中
Is the Datong volcanic group like that?
那個大同火山群有沒有像那個
Is there a record of such spontaneous pyroclastic activity at Yunhyen Volcano?
允賢火山這種自災性程度的火山碎屑的紀錄嗎
In history, in our human history, there is no
歷史上面 我們人類歷史上沒有
But in geology
但是在地質界
If you're interested, I can show you the trail where the debris flows
如果有興趣我可以帶你看那個碎屑流的路頭
what's that called
在那個叫什麼
There are several places where there are debris streams on the road.
好幾個地方有碎屑流的那種路頭
We haven't ordered that one yet
那一塊我們還沒有訂
We're just like 6,000 years now, just a volcanic ash date
我們現在只是像六千年只是訂一個火山灰的訂年
The dating on the other side of the debris flow has not been overcome
那碎屑流那邊的訂年這一塊還沒有克服
But at least there's evidence out there
但至少是有證據在外頭
is visible from the surface
就是在地表看得到
So I'm not sure if it's possible to be as serious as the suicide in Japan
所以還不確定是有可能像日本那種自殺性這麼嚴重的嗎
Are you sure you know there is such a record?
是還沒有確定知道有這個紀錄嗎
There is this record, but the history of our humanity is
有這個紀錄但是我們人類的歷史就是
In Taiwan, it is only possible that there will be no such records in a thousand years or more
在台灣只有可能一千年或多就沒有這些紀錄
ok thank you teacher
好謝謝老師
Hello teacher
老師好
Invite that Datong Volcanic Group because his age is quite old
請那個大通火山群因為他的年代也算蠻久的
there are two thousand
有兩千
More than 8 million to 200,000
800多萬到20萬
Recently, it was just about 50 million
最近是剛剛講的是5000萬左右
around 5000 years
5000年左右
So the distribution of a magma chamber in this place
所以這個地方的一個岩漿庫的分布
From a historical point of view, should it be centralized?
以歷史來看應該是不是集中的
because when it's about to spray flowers
因為它要噴花的時候
There must be cracks sucked out
必須要有裂吸出來
right
對
In the period of Big Butt Foshan in Triangular Broken City
在大臀佛山在三角斷城這個時期
Is it possible that there will be cracking and sucking out?
還有可能有裂吸會噴出來嗎
The volume of possible magma chambers relative to
可能岩漿庫的體積相對的
There must also be a match with the split suction
也必須要跟裂吸有一個搭配
So when it comes to spraying flowers
所以說要說到噴花
Is there one of these two
是不是這兩個有一個
a proof
一個印證性的東西
yes
是
Now many academic circles or our experts
現在很多學界或者我們專家
probably think it is
大概認為就是
The current triangular city
目前的三角斷城
It's actually a crack
其實它就是一個裂吸
The magma is likely to be on this fissure
那岩漿很可能就是在這個裂吸上面
this run up
這個跑上來
It is along this line of development
就是沿這個發育上來
In fact, we are not sure about the future.
那未來其實我們也不敢篤定
But the possibility is possible
但是這種可能性是有可能的
So on this trend along the triangular fault
所以在沿著三角斷層的這個走向上面
Seven Seven Three is right next to the Triangle Fault
七七三就在三角斷層的旁邊
The big oil pit is not far away
那大油坑也離不遠
We saw that seismic activity
我們看見那個地震的活動
As far as the seismic activity is concerned, it is on the side of the Seven Seventh Three Oil Pit.
就地震活動都在七七三大油坑這邊
It seems to be quite consistent with the geometry of the triangular fault.
跟三角斷層的那個幾何看起來還滿吻合的
So it's very likely along the fault knee of the Triangular Fault
所以是很有可能沿著三角斷層那個斷層帶的裂膝
Yan will come up
延將會上來
This is guesswork
這是推估啦
There is one and another inference that says
有一個還有一個推理就是說
because the triangular fault it belongs to a
因為三角斷層它是屬於一種
Only one thing on the earthquake fault will have a cracked knee
震斷層的一個東西才會有裂膝
Yeah
對對對
so many years till now
那多年來到現在
200,000 years to the last 50 million years
二十萬年到最近幾年的五千萬年
Because it is time in the crust to the geology
因為是時間在地殼來地質的那個來講
is it going to stabilize
它是不是去穩定
or there will be signs of activity
或者會有在活動的跡象
Research says there is a comparison problem with the magma chamber
研究說跟岩漿庫有一個比對的問題
Because if the magma chamber is on the other side
因為岩漿庫假如在那一頭
There can't be a problem with spraying at this end either.
這邊在這一頭也不可能有噴化的問題
Yes, this is actually a good question, that is
是 這個其實是一個好問題就是說
because of how we do research now
因為我們現在怎麼做的研究
mostly now
大部分就是現在
Then you have to compare with the past
那你要跟過去比
to know whether it is regionally stable or regionally unstable
才知道它是區域穩定還是區域不穩定
But the past evidence is actually super vague.
但是過去的證據其實超模糊的
So we just can't compare
所以我們就是無從比較
So many people say that the magma is in the process of cooling
所以有很多人講說岩漿是在冷卻的過程
Then of course nothing will happen in the future
那當然以後就沒有什麼事情
not cooling but warming
不是在冷卻是在增溫
Then we don't have good evidence to control this
那這個我們沒有很好的證據去控制
It is now moving up and down
它現在是往上還往下的活動的
yes yes yes of course
是 是 是 那當然
Because of the triangular triple island
因為三角三層島
Yes Yes Yes
是 是 是
There is still a lot of work to be done in this aftermath.
這個後戲還有很多工作還真的要繼續做
Thanks
謝謝
Hello Professor Li
李教授您好
two questions
兩個問題請教
The first one is like our landslides
第一個就是說像我們土石流
When we all have to issue alerts
我們都要發佈警戒的時候
Yellow alert when rainfall exceeds how much
雨量超過多少黃色警戒
Or the amount of rainfall exceeds the red alert
或者雨量超過多少紅色警戒
Don't know about our TVO
不曉得我們的TVO
Is there any data now
現在有沒有什麼數據
when the earthquake exceeds how much
當地震超過多少
or how much the ground temperature exceeds
或者地溫超過多少
or when the concentration of carbon dioxide reaches
或者二氧化碳濃度到多少的時候
we're going to issue an alert
我們要發佈警戒
We live right under the cape of the volcano
我們就住在火山山角下
we care about that
我們關心這一點
In addition, the second problem is the small travel pit
另外第二個問題就是小遊坑
We now call him to the mouth of the mouth
我們現在稱他到暴裂口的話
he didn't stand in burst
他沒有站在暴裂
Let's call him a blowout
我們稱他暴裂口比較好
Or call him Collapsing Fire
還是稱他叫崩塌地火
would be more appropriate
會比較恰當
First the second question should be the burst hole
先第二個問題應該是爆裂口
because ben he actually
因為奔他其實
because most of them think
因為大部分都覺得是
He's a breach in a fault zone
他是一個斷裂帶的一個爆裂口
that ben his behavior is not like that
那奔他的行為不是像那樣
ben he just offline
奔他只是下線
but he is a concave whole
但他是一個凹的整個
like a pit
像一個坑那樣
So it's not the same as his line
所以跟他線不太一樣
he is a blast
他是一個爆
so we have a lot to contend with
所以我們有很多爭氣
jet
噴氣
the first question is
那第一個問題是
vigilance
警戒
very difficult
非常的難
But NCDR is the center of the national battlefield
但是NCDR就是國家戰場中心
or the Executive Yuan or something like that
或者行政院什麼類似的
Forces me to talk about this every day
每天都逼著我要講這件事情
But I'm here to be honest
但是我在這裡老實講就是說
Actually, I know very little
其實我知道也很有限
But the people or the government need a standard
但是民眾或政府就需要一個標準
So what we are forced to do is a
所以我們被逼的就是一個
We try to have no history, no context
我們試著沒有歷史,沒有背景
So we don't know how crazy this volcano is before it erupts
所以我們不知道這個火山到什麼程度才會瘋才會噴發
If it has previous records we can probably use it as a reference
如果它有前面的紀錄我們大概就可以做參考
But we don't have any record of this
但是這個我們就沒有任何紀錄
So we can only put the compulsive ones on the other volcanoes
所以我們只能把強迫性的把其他的火山的
Many volcanoes in Japan are used as a reference
日本的很多火山拿來做一個參考
But I must say that this reference is really just for reference
但是我必須說這個參考其實真的僅做參考
cannot...
不能...
much is still unknown
好多還是未知
It is very difficult, because many people and most of the civil government have been asking about this matter
很難的事情,因為好多人都民間政府大部分都一直在問這件事情
this needs to be worked on
這個有待努力
the lady
這位女士
Mr. Lin, I would like to ask you for advice, because I often take Chinese and foreign tourists to small tourists
林老師我想請教你,因為我常常帶中外遊客去小遊客
I remember that there was a magnitude 5.5 earthquake about half a year ago this year
我記得大概半年前今年有一次5.5級的地震
very close to taipei
很靠近台北
In a few days, I will take tourists to Xiaoyoukeng
過幾天以後我帶遊客到小遊坑
I just realized I haven't gone yet
我就發現我還沒走到
I'm going to the parking lot
我一下停車場
I heard a loud noise like a jet plane
我就聽到像噴射飛機的很大的聲音
i never heard
我從來沒有聽過
wow you're the first to hear
哇 那你是第一個人聽到
I always
我一直
the airport is very big
飛機場非常大
Because I often take Chinese and foreign tourists to that scenic spot
因為我常常帶中外遊客到那個景點去
I've never heard of such a big
我從來沒有聽過這麼大的
as big as a jet plane right next to your ear
像噴射飛機就在你耳朵旁邊這麼大
I was thinking then
我那時候就在想說
My video should start leading everyone away
我視頻應該開始帶著大家逃
escape with everyone
帶著大家逃
But two months later
可是後來再過兩個月
when i go
我在去的時候
that voice is gone
那個聲音就不見
Then you often monitor over there
那你常常在那邊監測
i don't know
我不知道說
This is a very common phenomenon
這種是很常見的現象
it's just that loud
就是會有這麼大的聲音
The sound of that jet is different from what I usually go to
那個噴氣口的聲音跟往常我去的不一樣
The other one is that the information I read is that
那另外一個是我讀到的資料是說
Are the two judgments
兩個判斷是不是
Volcano
火火山
one that you just listed
一個是你剛剛有列出來
All I've read is that
我讀到的資料一直是說
two hundred thousand years
二十萬年
The first condition is two hundred thousand years
第一個條件是二十萬年
The second condition is
第二個條件是
Is there a magma chamber
有沒有岩漿庫
Then I know that the magma chamber
那我知道說岩漿庫
we now know there is
我們現在知道是有的
So we used to define it as repairing volcanoes
所以我們以前定義成修火山
or even a stone volcano
或甚至於石火山
Should be changed now, yes
現在都應該要改 是是是
Then I also read about Guishan Island
那我也讀到龜山島
The last eruption seems to be 200,000 years ago, isn't it?
最後一次噴發好像是20萬年前是不是
four times
有四次
then i want to know
那我想知道說
I compare the correct dating method
我比較正確的定年法
i should say
我應該講
which one should be used
應該用哪一個
Which one was the last eruption?
最後一次噴發是哪一個才對
Because I obviously 200,000 is out of the question
因為我顯然20萬是不可能
200,000 is not
20萬不是
ten thousand years
就是一萬年
Ten thousand years is actually related to the central
一萬年其實跟中央
the Geological Survey
那個地質調查所
active fault
他們用活動斷層
That is, the most active active fault is 10,000 years old.
就是最活躍的活動斷層就是一萬年
So ten thousand years is them
所以一萬年就是他們
In the geological world, they are equivalent to having a
就是地質界他們等於是有一個
As long as it is a living geological thing
只要是活的地質的東西
regardless of volcanic faults
不管火山斷層
10,000 is used as a reference
都是以一萬做參考
200,000 is too long
20萬太久了
200,000 that carbon
20萬那個那個碳
and you just heard me really
然後你剛剛聽到我真的
also hope that
還希望就是說
if you can take your time
你如果能把你的時間
probably tell me
大概跟我講
Because we now have a 24 hour record
因為我們現在有24小時紀錄
That
那
If you probably have, how often do you say
你如果大概有其實你說有多頻繁
In my impression, I watched it carefully for half a year
我印象中我仔細的看了半年
I spent a lot of time carefully
我花了滿多時間仔細
Just 20 hours of constant inspection
就是20小時一直檢查
About 10 days on average
平均大概10天
two weeks
兩個禮拜
Anyway, about 10 days or so
反正就是大概10天上下
I can probably add to the sound of this so-called place name
我大概就可以增加到有這種所謂地名的聲音
But sometimes very often
但是有時候會非常頻繁
Sometimes it's 3 days
有時候就是聯繫3天
always have
一直都有
sometimes sporadically
有時候就會偶發性的
Just once or twice a week
就是一個禮拜就一兩聲
so if you can really hear
所以你如果真的聽得到
Because I often ask people
因為我常常問人家說
Because of my information, I see that there is really
因為我資料我看到真的有
but i didn't really hear anyone
但是我沒有真正有人聽到過
So you probably have this very precious
所以你大概這個是滿珍貴的
is that I believe he usually looks like
就是我相信他平常看起來就是
just pissed off
就是就是冒氣
But sporadically there will be something like
但是偶發性的會有像
like firecrackers
像鞭炮那樣的
loud this
很大聲的這個
exploded
炸開了
Otherwise, I can't receive the earthquake
否則我那地震已經收不到
like an ice cream machine
像冰激機
that should be
那應該就是
What you describe is that it is relatively low frequency
你描述的就是它是比較低頻的
then a little longer
然後比較長一點的時間
very double
很雙重
Yeah
對對對
and heavy
而且很重
wow this is very
哇 這個很
yes
是
volcanic words
火火山的話
fire volcano it is very common words
火火山它是很普通的話
can there be a way
能不能有個方法
can make it a stone volcano
能夠讓它成為石火山
Is it right
對嗎
because it is said to be in the volcano
因為說它在火火山
while it's working
它在運作的時候
we invest something in
我們投資一些東西進去
Yes or no
是不是
then to destroy it
然後來破壞它
reduce it fire volcano regulations
減少它火火山的規定
this is feasible
這個是可行的
but is it possible to do
但是是不是能夠做到
this
這個
this is a bit difficult
這個有點難
like an earthquake some people say
就像地震有些人說
shock energy failed
震撼能量失敗
So this fault
所以這個斷層
he just wanted to say
他就想說
we just let it
我們就讓它
small earthquake
小地震
A big earthquake turns into many small earthquakes
大地震變成很多小地震
we water it
我們把它灌水
this is science
這個是科學的事
fault
斷層
you pump it in
你把它打水進去
it will start to slide and release energy
它就會開始滑,就釋放能量
But this is very risky, no one dares to do it, why?
但是這個非常風險很大,沒有人敢這樣做,為什麼?
Yes, usually it is fine, if you add water to it, it will cause a big earthquake, who will be responsible
對,平常它反而沒事,你把它加水去,它來一個大地震,誰負責
In fact, you can't control it's potion, it's still potion
這個其實你沒辦法控制它的藥劑,還是藥劑
The same problem, that is, the natural world of volcanoes, I think it may be difficult for us
同樣的問題,就是說火山那個大自然界,我覺得我們大概很難吧
With current technology it is possible
在目前的科技上面可能
Because the magma chamber is over there.
因為岩漿庫就在那邊啊
It should be said that it is possible, but I don't know how to do it now
應該是說有可能,但是現在不曉得怎麼做
Yes
是的
You just mentioned that Yellowstone is a giant volcano
您剛剛有提到黃石公園是一個超大的火山
How is the so-called super large, medium or small volcano defined?
那所謂的超大或是中型或是小型火山是怎麼定義
So how dangerous is it?
那它的危害程度大概是怎麼樣
Probably it is easy for us to define it now, just look at the magma household
大概我們現在很容易界定就是看它岩漿戶
Like this volume of the magma house
像岩漿戶的這個體積
Like the one in Yellowstone Park, maybe
像黃石公園那個好像大概
Seems like thousands of cubic kilometers
好像是幾千個立方公里
A few thousand, not like fifteen thousand or so
幾千喔 不像一千五還是多少
It just looks like our big round volcano may only be
那剛剛像我們那個其實大輪火山可能只有
Only a hundred, about a hundred Cheng Qi
只有百而已啦 大概百左右的程齊
Of course, the bigger the magma household
那當然就岩漿戶越大
It only takes a little bit of it to be quite impressive
它只要幾出一點點其實就很可觀
If the magma household is small
那岩漿戶如果小的話
Of course it is less dangerous
它當然就危險就很小
So volcanoes are graded
所以火山它們有分級啦
It is divided into one, two, three, four, and five grades according to the magma
它根據那個岩漿的那個分了一二三四五級
many graded
很多有分級
there is a child
有一個小朋友
Just now I saw a few after the volcanic eruption
剛剛前面有看到幾個是火山噴發之後
Residents have examples of fleeing
居民有逃離的例子
Then I want to ask that after the volcano ceases to be active
那我想問那火山停止活動之後
How soon can they go back and live there
他們多久才可以回去那邊生活
wow, this is another problem
哇 這個又是一個難題喔
In fact, the volcano told people to evacuate
其實火山叫民眾撤離
relatively easy
相對的比較容易
and then after evacuation
然後一撤離以後
when can we let people go back
哪時候能讓人家回去
People in general always want to go back
一般民眾都一直想回去
it looks like as long as it doesn't smoke
看起來只要不冒煙
he just wants to go back
他就想回去
But the role unit, the government, is actually very difficult
可是角色單位 政府其實非常難
because just said
因為就剛剛講的
when people go up
人家往上竄的時候
We can easily see those steps
我們很容易看得到那些步驟
But he scurried to a certain word
但是他竄竄竄到某個字
Then start writing...
然後就開始文...
when there is no change
就是沒有在變化的時候
When will it suddenly rise again
哪時候會再突然又再竄起來
In fact, the politics started to be very blurred
其實那個政治就開始很模糊
even say when it will start to be quiet
甚至說哪時候會開始安靜
no good reference
沒有很好的參考標準
sometimes in absolute units
有時候是絕對單位的
it's just a decision
就是一個決定而已
So going back is actually a big trouble
所以回去其實是一個很大的麻煩
when can we go back
就是哪時候可以回去
like hawaii, right?
就像夏威夷對不對
move at midnight
午夜那時候動動動
then it seems to stop
然後就好像停了
recently again
最近又來
like that paris island
像那個巴黎島也是一樣
Last October was like two months of activity
去年10月就好像有兩個月活動
Then it stops in the middle
然後這個中間就停了
That July the last July
那7月最近7月
Paris Island is back in action
巴黎島又開始活動起來
So when it starts moving
所以當一開始動的時候
That kind of estimation is actually more difficult.
那種預估其實就比較難
But from being quiet to moving
但是從安靜變成要動
It's actually easier
其實是比較容易
from motion to silence
從動要變成安靜
that is
就是
not so easy
不是那麼容易
so still need a lot
所以還是要很多
lady behind
小姐在後面
I just want to ask
就是我想請問一下
that researcher is
那個研究員就是
Because I told you a long time ago
因為之前很久以前我講過說
Earthquakes can be predicted with animals
地震可以用動物來預測
like a fish or a snake or something
就是好比魚或蛇或什麼
But have you ever thought about using animals?
但是有沒有想過就是用動物來進行
I don't know it's probably not practical either
我不知道這可能也不太實際
but maybe there is a way
但或許是個方法
Have you ever been through this period?
你有經歷過這一段嗎
still have you thought about it
還是你有想過
this is good
這個不錯喔
It's the earthquake why we use animals
就是地震為什麼我們要用動物
in what strange way
用什麼奇奇怪的方法
Because the science of earthquake prediction
因為以地震預測科學上面
At the scientific level, everyone feels that it is not feasible yet.
科學的層面大家覺得還沒有可行
So everyone is that if you go to a western doctor
所以大家就是你如果去找西醫
I found out that you are terminally ill and cannot be cured.
發現說你這個是絕症不能救
Then everyone finds a way, right?
然後大家就找偏方對不對
But in terms of volcanoes
但是以火山的話
He tells you about science
他就科學這樣跟你講說
If the volcano wants a prescription
火山要偏方的話
there is a lot of evidence
就有很多證據的
Why should I look for a remedy?
我幹嘛去找偏方呢
So in terms of volcanoes
所以以火山的話
You do these monitoring for formal evidence
你就正規證據的做這些監測
probably the answer
大概就可以達到答案的
But the earthquake is still touching
但是地震就是還在摸手
Thousands of dollars and ideas will come out
千幾百塊的想法就會出來
Thanks
謝謝
I want to confirm one thing with your professor
我想向您教授確認一件事情
months ago
幾個月前
There was an earthquake at more than four o'clock in Beitou
在北投有一個四點多的地震
Exactly the same result when I saw
正一樣結果我看的時候
It seems to be near Zhongshan Building
是好像在中山樓附近
That's very close to the volcanoes in the big picture
那離那個大圖的火山群很近
Later, the Meteorological Bureau said that it was due to the movement of the plate.
後來氣象局說是那個板塊移動的關係
but i doubt it
但是我覺得很懷疑
so according to your opinion
所以根據您的意見
The earthquake caused by the same thing
那一次的正一樣所引起的地震
Is it really a plate movement?
到底是真的是板塊移動
Or a shock from the volcanoes
還是火山群的一個震撼
if i remember correctly
我如果沒記錯
you may be asking to have a
你可能是問有一個
They called it the Beitou Earthquake at first
他們一開始說叫北投地震
It's about five o'clock
這規模五點幾
Because for many years Taipei City has not
因為很多年來台北市沒有
the same earthquake that happened
正一樣發生過的地震
The earthquake was actually reported by the Meteorological Bureau.
那那個地震其實是氣象局講的
There should be nothing wrong, the reason is that the earthquake was more than 100 kilometers deep
應該是沒有錯 原因是那個地震很深 100多公里
So that is the earthquake of the plate that is on the screen with our Philippine Sea plate going north.
所以那個是跟我們菲律賓海板塊往北螢幕在這個螢幕帶的板塊的地震
It's not on the very shallow surface of the volcano this 10 kilometers
它不是在火山的這個10公里這個很淺的地表
If it's at 5km 10km it's more to do with volcanoes
如果它是在5公里10公里 那就是跟火山比較有關係
But is it 140 or what? 140 kilometers, it is very deep, and it has something to do with the plate
但是它是140還是多少 140公里 那是很深是跟板塊有關係
So this explanation from the Meteorological Bureau is basically OK.
所以氣象局這種解釋是基本上是OK的
It is accepted by science
就是就是科學上面是接受的
hello mr behind
喂先生在後面
Hello, Mr. Lin, what I want to ask is, as far as we know, the threat of volcanoes in northern Taiwan
林老師您好 我想問的是啊 就我們所知道在臺灣北部的火山的威脅
In addition to the Big Butt Volcano, the undersea volcano in Keelung is also a volcanic volcano
除了大臀火山之外 在基隆的海底火山它也是火火山
And it may have been active in Keelung Sea School in 1867
而且它可能在1867年的基隆大海校是有活動的
In the future, will we target such
那未來我們會不會針對這樣的
Disaster risk will do some scientific research
災害風險會做一些科學上的研究
Thanks
謝謝
Yes, I'm personally very interested
會 我個人就非常有興趣
You are actually many, many professional
你其實就很多很多專業的
It is because of Keelung Port
就是因為基隆港
that
那個
Below Zheng there is a seabed and there is a volcano
鄭下方就有個海底就有個火山
submarine volcano
海底火山
And they do ocean exploration
而且他們去做海洋的探測
That volcano will still have majestic
那個火山還會有貌企
It means it's a volcano
代表那是火火山
That teacher Xi Zhiwen from CUHK
那個中大的習志文老師
And that National Taiwan University teacher Yang Shanghai
還有那個台大楊上海老師
they just do some research
他們就做一些調查
Then I also believe
然後我也很相信
I personally believe
我個人很相信
this has to be confirmed
這個要證實
It was the tsunami in 1867
就是1867年那一次的海嘯
Probably
很可能是
Because it was said earlier that the tsunami caused by the earthquake
因為早期都說地震造成的海嘯
but the volcano
但是火山
Tsunamis caused by submarine volcanic activity
海底火山活動造成的海嘯
In fact, the possibility is quite high
其實可能性蠻高的
but need evidence
但是需要證據
that we need to investigate
就是我們需要做調查
So this piece of the future
所以這一塊未來
the government does too
政府也去做
I personally would
我個人也會
will be very involved in doing it
會很投入去做
It's just that the investigation and research in the sea is more difficult
只是在海裡的調查研究比較難
so we need
所以我們需要
more of these techniques
更多的這些技術
or some way to
或者一些方法才能
It's hard work I'm worth doing
很刻苦 我很值得做的東西
yes
是
Hello teacher, those two questions
老師好 那個兩個問題
The first question is about the prediction of volcanic eruptions
第一個問題是關於火山爆發的預測
It's what you just mentioned
就是您剛剛有提到就是說
If you try to predict a volcanic eruption
如果盡量預測火山爆發的話
We can see that it was before the earthquake
我們可以看就是地震的生前
It is possible to slowly change forward from a relatively deep place
就是可能從比較深的地方慢慢變前
Then but what I want to ask is
然後但是我想要問的是
The speed at which the magma is extruded from the ground
這個岩漿從地底擠出來的這個速度
how fast it can
它能夠多快
If a whole bunch of predictions today happen within two hours
如果今天一大堆預測都在兩個小時之內發生
Like what kind of hot spring water becomes hot?
像什麼溫泉水變燙啊
or place names
或者是地名之類的
just too helpless
就是太沒有辦法
could it be in two hours
它有沒有可能是在兩個小時
maybe or within an hour
可能或是一個小時之內就會
It's all ordinary earthquakes
就是全部平凡地震 地名
Then the water temperature of the hot springs and the like
然後溫泉的水溫奏生之類
Is it possible to have such a fast speed
就是有沒有可能有這麼快的速度
This is the first question
這是第一個問題
Excuse me
不好意思
Then the second question is
然後第二個問題是
about that fire pot
關於那個火口壺
that's me in the magazine
就是我之前在雜誌上
That is, there are three crater lakes in Africa.
就是非洲有三座 三個火口湖
Then what used to happen was
然後曾經發生過的事情是
It's the volcano under the crater lake.
就是那個火口湖下方的火山
It's the gas that erupts and causes
就是氣體噴發 然後造成
carbon dioxide in the lake
湖泊裡面的二氧化碳
What concentration is saturated or something like that?
什麼濃度飽和什麼之類的
And then this carbon dioxide floats out of this lake
然後這個二氧化碳就飄出了這個湖泊
and killed an entire village in one night
然後在一個晚上之內就殺死了整個村莊的人
Then what I want to ask is
那我想要請問就是
Is it possible for this to happen in Taiwan?
台灣有可能發生這種事情嗎
because we just heard
因為我們剛剛有聽到
That is, Taiwan has submarine volcanoes.
就是台灣是有海底火山的
There are many hot springs I don't know
還有很多溫泉我不知道
Is it because Taiwan has this condition that this kind of thing will happen?
就是台灣有這個條件會發生這種事情嗎
that's it thank you
就這樣 謝謝
The first question is to say
第一個問題就是說
will it be one hour two hours
會不會一個小時兩個小時
Suddenly the volcano erupts
突然就火山噴發
basically it should be hard
基本上應該是很難
Because the magma actually moves its body
因為岩漿其實它的台身移動
It's actually very sticky
其實是很粘稠
it won't be like a bomb
它不會像炸彈一樣
Run from 5 kilometers to 10 kilometers to the surface in one go
一下從5公里10公里就跑到地表
can't be that fast
不可能那麼快速
usually a few weeks
通常就是幾個禮拜
months or even years
幾個月甚至有到幾年都有
it pants slowly
它就慢慢地喘
So within a short period of time
所以很短時間一天以內
It should be theoretically not
應該是從學理上面是沒有
about crater lake
那有關火口湖
Actually that's because
其實那個因為是
It's a volcano full of camps
就是滿點營的火山
there is a crater
就是有火山口
like a lake
就好像一個湖泊
Then there will be a lot of water
然後就會下很多的水
that volcanic gas
那那個火山氣體
In fact, a lot of acid
其實很多有流酸
And CO2 is the most
還有CO2是最多
There is also a lot of acid
流酸也滿多的
So these can easily become sour
所以這些很容易就會變成酸
carbonic acid
碳酸 流酸這些
Of course for plant organisms
那當然對於植物生物
Or animals actually have a lot of influence
或者動物其實影響滿大
so you just have to be in crater lake
所以你只要在火山口湖
if there is volcanic activity
如果真的有火山活動的話
In fact, the water will become very acidic.
那其實那個水都會變得很酸
will affect
會影響
But under the sea
但是在海底下的話
This problem may be less
這個問題可能就比較小
Because the sea is water after all, it is big
因為海畢竟是水是很大的
so it will be diluted
所以它會被會稀釋掉
but
但是
There is little water in the lake
湖的話水量很少
So it will be relatively high concentration
所以它就會比較濃度很高
will be more harmful
才會比較傷害
The sea area probably
那海域大概
Unless it happens to be in an undersea crater
除非是剛好在海底火山口的
Creatures there may be affected
那裡的生物可能會受影響
But it's easy to dilute
不過還是很容易稀釋掉的
There's another one here
這邊還有一位
Hello teacher
老師好
What about Datong Volcano?
請問大同火山呢
Our year with the Giant Volcano Society is
我們這跟巨火山會的地年是
The last climb was within a few thousand years
最後一次攀發在幾千年以內
then ask the teacher
那請問老師
The year of the Volcano Society is
火山會的地年是
probably what kind of method
大概要是什麼樣的方法
may the teacher explain
可以請老師解釋一下嗎
volcano will it actually be
火山會它其實就
There are many of them are simple to use
有簡單他們都很多就用
carbon fourteen
碳十四
some of its half lives
它的一些半衰期
So many address fields use
所以很多地址界都是用
use half-life
用半衰期
then it is a
那它就是一個
a decay it takes
一個衰減它需要
how many years then see if it is
多少年然後看它是
The ratio is attenuated several times
比例是衰減了幾次
then how many years
然後就多少年
It's probably like this for many years
很多地年大概就是這樣
that's the place to use that half-life
那是用那個半衰期的地點
The half-life of course
那半衰期當然有
Carbon stone is often used for thousands of years to ten thousand years
碳石是比較幾千年到萬年常常被用的
But if it's hundreds of thousands of years or millions
但是如果是幾十萬年或百萬
It has another life-releasing business that it can do
它有另外的這個放生業業可以做
Make nails or teeth
做甲牙或是牙牙之類的
So they have professionals who are doing this
所以他們有專業有人在做這一塊的
yes
是
Do you have
有沒有
well here is the last one
好這邊有最後一位
last question
最後一個問題
I just want to ask
就是我想請問一下
that pyroclastic
那個火山碎械流
Can you predict the direction
可不可以預知方向
because at that time
因為那時候
Pompeii will be submerged by pyroclastic flow
龐貝古城會被火山碎械流淹沒
That is, it goes in that direction
也就是它從那個方向過去
And then there's another
然後另外還有另外的
neapolitan place
拿波理式的地方
if it's like taipei
那如果像是台北
Words distributed by Datong Volcano
大同火山分發的話
can we just be
我們可不可以就是
predict which direction it will go
預知它往哪個方向
Then we can avoid that disaster
然後我們可以避免掉那個災害
yes
是
the answer is yes
答案是可以的
It's as simple as water
很簡單就是就跟水一樣
you pour the water down
你把水一潑下去
it goes to the lowest flow
它就是往那個最低的流
In fact, for this, like Japan, especially Japan, a lot of work has been done.
那其實為了這個其實像日本特別日本做了很多工作
For example, he looked at the village, that, that, the ancient ground is the village
他比如說看那個村莊那個那個那個古地下來就是村莊
then what do they do
然後他們怎麼辦
The taxes flowed down and rushed to the village
那個那個稅稅流下來就沖到村莊
They make something like this gutter or retaining wall
他們就做類似這個排水溝或者擋土牆
It’s a bit like the concept of flood control, which is to be a very, very resolute body.
就是有點像防洪那個概念就是做一個很很很堅毅的體那樣
When the tax flow comes to meet that body, he will turn the corner
那稅稅流來碰到那個體他就拐彎了
won't rush to the village
就不會沖到村莊
So this can be predicted and pre-cast.
所以這個可以預測可以預施啦
Then make some preparations for evacuation
然後做一些避難的一些準備
So Japan has done a lot in this regard
所以日本在這方面做了非常多
yes
是
good
好
it's almost time
這時間就差不多了
i want to end
我想在結束之前
uh bring back the preview
呃帶回預告一下
Our feast of knowledge next month in August
我們八月份下個月的知識饗宴
by Chen Zhicheng
是由陳志成研究員
Institute of Biomedical Sciences
是本院生物醫學科學研究所
What's the matter with soreness?
要主講的是酸痛是怎麼回事
So this is a life science subject
所以這是一個生命科學的題材
Let's Talk Slowly
要慢談痛絕分子社
Human figure and acid receptor molecule
人物學與酸的受體分子
before all of us are ready to leave
那在我們的大家準備離開之前
Let's give another round of applause
讓我們再度以熱烈的掌聲
Thank you for the wonderful speech today
謝謝今天的精采演講
good
好
Thank you all for coming
謝謝大家的光臨